<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The natural fanatick, or, Reason consider'd in its extravagancy in religion and (in some late treatises) usurping the authority of the Church and councils by John Warly ...</title>
            <author>Warly, John, d. 1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 172 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 117 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67621</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W876</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15139</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13144566</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13144566</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98034</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67621)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98034)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 780:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The natural fanatick, or, Reason consider'd in its extravagancy in religion and (in some late treatises) usurping the authority of the Church and councils by John Warly ...</title>
                  <author>Warly, John, d. 1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 215 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by Thomas Basset ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: prelim. p. [16].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Faith.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98034:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98034:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Natural FANATICK, OR, Reaſon Conſider'd In its Extravagancy in RELIGION, and (in ſome late Treatiſes) Uſurping the Authority of the Church and Councils,</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN WARLY</hi> B.D. late Fellow of <hi>Clare-Hall</hi> in <hi>Cambridg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Sic ſi homines rationem bono conſilio a Diis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalibus datam, in fraud m malitiam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertunt, non dari illam, quam dari humano generi melius fuit:</hi>
               </q> 
               <bibl>Cicer. de nat. Deor. lib. 3. </bibl> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Satius fuerit nullam omnino nobis a Dijs immortalibus datam eſſe rationem, quam tantam cum pernicie datam, ibidem.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>Thomas Baſſet</hi> at the <hi>George</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> 1676.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:98034:2"/>
            <p>IMPRIMATUR.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>2. Novemb. 1675.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Geo. Hooper</hi> R<hi rend="sup">mo.</hi> D<hi rend="sup">no.</hi> Arch. <hi>Cant.</hi> à Sacr. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticis.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:98034:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable HENEAGE Lord FINCH, Baron of <hi>DAVENTRY</hi> AND Lord High Chancellor of <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Lordſhip</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough Dedications as much as Prefaces may ſeem formal imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencies; yet they ceaſe to be ſuch when the Patronage it as the <hi>Broad Seal of England,</hi> to Authorize and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence the Examination of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertine; though in ſuch method as may ſeem unkind and unnatural to Humanity in the diſcovery of Reaſons defect, and expoſing it to
<pb facs="tcp:98034:3"/>the publick vieu <hi>naked</hi> and <hi>intoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated.</hi> This way of arguing is ſo far juſtifiable as it is more neceſſary at ſome times to declare that men are <hi>mad, ſools,</hi> and <hi>bewitch'd</hi> in their ſearch for Religion, than to flatter them with ſoft compellations of men of <hi>ſober minds,</hi> diſpos'd for <hi>reaſonable ſervice,</hi> and critically <hi>wiſe to Salvation.</hi> This method is alſo commended by Chriſt's pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, who diſputing with the <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees</hi> and <hi>Opinionative formaliſts</hi> of the <hi>Jewiſh Church,</hi> anſwers their queſtions with queſtions, and at the ſame time confounded them whilſt he inform'd them by retort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their folly, and turning the edge of their own troubleſom queries on themſelves; which was the moſt
<pb facs="tcp:98034:3"/>proper way to ſilence a <hi>Pragmatical Jew.</hi> The preſent ſtate of Religion as it is to be found in <hi>factions minds</hi> makes this method ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for this age, which is ful of <hi>Rea: ſoning</hi> Zelots <hi>(the ſecular Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks)</hi> who muſt be Catechiz'd in the firſt Elements of their <hi>natural Religion,</hi> though in a <hi>ſtile</hi> as <hi>rough</hi> as that by which <hi>Arnobius</hi> diſcovered the folly of the <hi>Gentiles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe conſiderations, I hope, may render this bold addreſs more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable, and the Tract leſs liable to cenſure, which being preſum'd I cannot but think it neceſſary, that I declare which were the first motives which conmended the task to my thoughts, and what directed it to your moſt <hi>Honourable Patronage
<pb facs="tcp:98034:4"/>Libertiniſm</hi> exalting it ſelf above <hi>Sacred Authority,</hi> and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurping its power, pleading <hi>Reaſons claim</hi> and right to the <hi>ſpiritual Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;</hi> and it being ſeaſonably checkt by that <hi>Oration</hi> which made <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> (in its Repreſentatives) its Auditor, when it captivated both <hi>ear</hi> and <hi>mind</hi> with <hi>ſweetneſs</hi> and <hi>vigour,</hi> and (as it is the property of Eloquence) <hi>commanded whilſt it perſwaded:</hi> I thought it would not appear an impertinent peice of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity in a private perſon to inquire into, and examin the compoſition of that <hi>Leaven</hi> with which Faction <hi>ſwells,</hi> and <hi>turbulently ſerments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I was alſo more confident in this addreſs to your Lordſhip, whilſt I conſider'd that ſome of the matter
<pb facs="tcp:98034:4"/>of theſe papers, when ſpoken, as duty call'd me, as well as written, found encouragement from the Right Honourable <hi>Heneage</hi> Earl of <hi>Winchilſea</hi> my very good Lord; preſuming they might find the ſame favourable entertainment whilſt they apply themſelves to the <hi>ſame name,</hi> which is now famous both for Forreign and Domeſtick admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the affairs of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; For it is no contradiction in my hopes to conclude that <hi>Souls</hi> may be allied as well as <hi>bodies,</hi> and that there may be Affinity of <hi>Opinions</hi> as well as <hi>Perſons:</hi> and the ſame ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular <hi>Candour</hi> and <hi>Humanity</hi> may run in the ſame <hi>blood</hi> as <hi>Hereditary</hi> to the <hi>Family.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Task was alſo encouraged
<pb facs="tcp:98034:5"/>as neceſſary, whilſt I conſiderd that ſeveral <hi>intereſted perſons</hi> cloakt their practiſe under the <hi>thin film</hi> of a pretended Religion, which might exempt them from the imputation of being <hi>Atheiſts</hi> (which is a name ſo odious as would effectually ſtifle their deſigns and make their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe nauſeous) and ſeem'd careleſs whether Chriſtian Religion, as it is ſaid of <hi>Aſtraea,</hi> return'd again to heaven; ſo that the world was poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed with a belief that they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged the Deity which they would have <hi>prov'd</hi> and <hi>worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped</hi> by their <hi>rational Method.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that ſuch might not impoſe upon credulous minds, by perſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them they are truly Religious. I thought it proper to unmask them,
<pb facs="tcp:98034:5"/>by ſhewing that they are ſo far from being ſo, that by that method they cannot intitle themſelves to the names of <hi>Theiſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe men alſo pleas'd themſelves, or at leaſt others (with an empty name of a <hi>new kind</hi> of <hi>faith,</hi> which they did no more underſtand than the <hi>Exorciſt</hi> doth the <hi>Sacred words</hi> abus'd in his <hi>Charm</hi>) <hi>making it natural Reaſon with an object brought nigher by Revelation,</hi> and to ſupply its defect have impudently medled with the object <hi>God</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf repreſenting him as a <hi>Proteus</hi> to be ador'd in ſeveral ſhapes, or as a Picture to be ſeen and worſhipped in divers forms according to the various ſituation of the Spectators, by which arbitrary <hi>Transſiguration</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in each mans brain <hi>he</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:98034:6"/>will be as much abus'd in mens phancies as the Deity was in the Heathens Idolatrous way of worſhip. It need not be call'd to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips mind that ſuch extravagant liberty will exceed all former Her eſie and ſchiſm, which ſeem more modeſt, for they were never contracted into a more narrow compaſs than an <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, or congregation,</hi> but this makes (in its Eccleſiaſtical Anar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy) <hi>each Zelot an independent-Church</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I was not only led to this Task by the <hi>wild projects</hi> of <hi>Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant brains,</hi> but by the practice of men of more ſober minds, who (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) obſerving the <hi>predominant humour</hi> and <hi>prevailing prejudices</hi> of ſome againſt <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> as Tyrannical over Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences,
<pb facs="tcp:98034:6"/>out of their great zeal for the Church, and Chriſtian reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (like <hi>Commanders</hi> diſarm'd in ſight ſnatch a Sword from their Enemies hand, when ill ſucceſs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived them of their own) diſpute with the <hi>Atheiſt</hi> upon his <hi>own prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> and fight againſt him with his arguments, which way hath been little ſuccesful. And it is no great wonder, for <hi>Divine Authority</hi> (which is excluded in ſuch diſputes) ſets the <hi>edge</hi> on the <hi>ſpiritual ſword,</hi> &amp; is the ſtrength of that <hi>arm</hi> which <hi>weilds</hi> it. All natural arguments ſo managed are as ſome <hi>vitious Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſms</hi> which have all the <hi>propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> but <hi>concluded</hi> nothing. But this being not ſo eaſily believ'd as ſaid in This Treatiſe, <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> diſpute their rights to be
<pb facs="tcp:98034:7"/>judg in ſpiritual matters. This method is altogether neceſſary: for the Reaſoner will never believe he is lawfully condemn'd, if he have not liberty to bring in all <hi>natural evidence</hi> in the <hi>Trial,</hi> which large conceſſion will make him know the vanity of liberty falſly ſo call'd, and ſubjugate his unruly mind, playing like a fiſh which is wearied with the <hi>line</hi> of his vain imaginations, who ſcorn'd all <hi>ties</hi> of <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Religion.</hi> As ſubjection to Governours is never more effectually recommended by any mere <hi>rational argument</hi> than that which comes with this conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the neceſſity of bring obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to Magiſtrates, becauſe <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature</hi> is not ſo able to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid for it ſelf in <hi>ſolitude</hi> as in <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:98034:7"/>So the extravagant <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners</hi> in Religion are not any way better reduced to obedience to Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Authority, than by contemplating the vanity of their own imaginations. For that proſpect of their own ignorance will make Reaſon ſo <hi>obſequious</hi> and <hi>tame,</hi> that though Eccleſiaſtical Laws (as the Greek Law-giver ſaies of Laws in general) are lookt on as <hi>Cobwebs;</hi> yet they will not think it their <hi>intereſt</hi> to break them.</p>
            <p>This conſider'd, I hope may ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plant all cenſure which might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn this way of arguing as preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial to Religion by rendring ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, which were deſign'd to fortifie it, weakned by <hi>too ſevere an inquiſition,</hi> for this method doth no more violence to Religion, than a
<pb facs="tcp:98034:8"/>Chirurgion doth to his Patient whilſt he <hi>ſtretches</hi> the <hi>Sinews</hi> in order to <hi>ſet a bone</hi> which was out of its place. Neither ſhall I fear that theſe Papers will be lookt upon as vainly ſpeculative, ſeeing the <hi>Dedication</hi> directs the Reader to ſo eminent an <hi>Example,</hi> which alone (though the Church was not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected by <hi>civil power</hi> and <hi>truth na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked</hi> in that ſenſe which the <hi>factious Adverſary</hi> would have it) is able to <hi>win</hi> practice and <hi>engage</hi> all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian obedience, which is deſired and deſign'd, (ſo far as theſe Papers can promote it) <hi>by</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My L<hi rend="sup">d.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <signed>
               <hi>Your Lordſhips moſt humble and obedient Servant</hi> John Warly. </signed>
         </div>
         <div type="authors_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:98034:8"/>
            <head>An Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>SO often as the word <hi>Reaſoner</hi> oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currs in this Tract, it is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of the Author of the Treatiſe of <hi>Humane Reaſon</hi> or of any other who is conducted by his principles, and ſo often as the word <hi>Reconciler</hi> is us'd, it is to be underſtood of the Author of the conſiderations of <hi>the Reconcileable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Reaſon and Religion,</hi> other Authors antient and Modern are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther plainly cited or ſo diſcoverable by their matter, that nothing more need be ſaid by way of Explanation.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:98034:9"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>REad as ſtreight an Union <hi>page</hi> 16. for who <hi>read</hi> which <hi>p.</hi> 34. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>p.</hi> 35. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. 65. dele they 73. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>p.</hi> 83. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>p.</hi> 85 <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>p.</hi> 90. <hi>r.</hi> terminated <hi>p.</hi> 92. <hi>r.</hi> &amp; <hi>p.</hi> 104 <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 108 <hi>r. Minucius Felix</hi> 112. dele that 115. <hi>r.</hi> as much <hi>p.</hi> 116. dele leaſt <hi>r.</hi> or <hi>p.</hi> 118. <hi>r.</hi> Erroneous <hi>p.</hi> 139. dele not and <hi>r.</hi> are not <hi>p.</hi> 153. <hi>r.</hi> ſcales <hi>p.</hi> 162. for which <hi>r.</hi> when 170 <hi>r.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>p.</hi> 173. for that <hi>r.</hi> what 178. fornor <hi>r.</hi> now, <hi>p.</hi> 180. Dele not 184.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98034:9"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>EASON in ſome late Treatiſes being ſet up Umpire in Religion, challenging Appeals to be made to it, as the higheſt Tribunal, and being aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with priviledges, which are exalted above <hi>Pelagian</hi> invention, or what any other Hereſie could project. And one Article of the Church of <hi>England</hi> being threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by ſome poſitions which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly oppoſe it, by ſaying; <hi>That a man may be ſav'd by the Law or
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98034:10"/>Sect which he profeſſeth, ſo that he diligently frame his life according to that Law, and the light of nature.</hi> I thought my ſelf obliged to examine the foundation on which this natural infallibility was built, which is ſupported by theſe poſitions, which ſay; <hi>That faith is an aſſent given to Religious matters, the underſtanding and will being no otherwiſe aſſiſted, than they are in drawing other Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And that Reaſon requires no other aſſiſtance in the act of faith, than the propoſal of that which is to be believed, which the Reaſoner calls the near approach of the object being brought nigher by Revelation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The former account of faith is
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98034:10"/>imperfect, and attended with many falſe concluſions, which are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions from it; amongſt many, let this be conſidered; That no man (according to that deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of faith) can be an Infidel, who hath readholy Scripture, or its contents or matter propoſed to his underſtanding; And as it is an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility that <hi>Euclid</hi> ſhould not render the intelligent Reader a <hi>Mathematician,</hi> ſo it is equally impoſſible, that the contents of holy Scriptures propoſed to the Infidel, ſhould not make him a Convert: This is neceſſarily infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the former poſition, and ſhall be more illuſtrated by a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; ſuppoſe therefore an <hi>Ethnic</hi> made ſo much a Proſelite
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98034:11"/>to the true Religion by reading holy Scriptures, that he gives aſſent to matters of Religion no further, than upon Examination he ſhall find them agreeable or congenial to his Reaſon, or (to ſpeak another Phraſe,) <hi>Reaſon can confeſs them to be true:</hi> and let him be ſuppos'd to ſpeak like the <hi>Samaritan</hi>-Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in another caſe; ſaying, I do not believe the Creation of the World, the incarnation of Chriſt, and other matters of faith, becauſe of the evidence of the Divine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, but becauſe I preſume my belief will be ratifi'd and approv'd by my reaſon, which is naturally bound to confeſs them, when they are propos'd, it will appear upon experiment, that he is a wavering
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98034:11"/>and weak Convert, not far re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd from infidelity. This ſuppoſition is agreeable to the Reaſoners account of faith, and that term of art which expreſſeth it, calling <hi>under ſtanding and will the Elements of which faith is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded.</hi> In examining which I intend not to be ſo critical as he, in interpretation of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> will equally admit of ſuch criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal exerciſe, but rather take it in the common acceptation. <hi>That out of which bodies are made, and into which is their laſt Return or Reſolution;</hi> which, being accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated to the Reaſoners ſenſe, will conclude, that Religious knowledge was no otherwiſe in mans mind than <hi>Idaea's:</hi> or ſome
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98034:12"/>dormantknowledg to be excited by propoſal of holy Scriptures, or as letters to make words to be fram'd by the Divine <hi>Paedagogy,</hi> the Law and Goſpel too being in his ſenſe but as a School-maſter (not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Apoſtles meaning) to prompt the underſtanding. This is ſo falſe, that it may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed by Hiſtory, which ſayes, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny peruſed the Moſaical-Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſome paſt critical judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on them. <hi>Longinus,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, with the <hi>Greek</hi> Law-givers (though ſome of their knowledg ſeems borrowed from them) who muſt be in the Catalogue of Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels. And later ages give ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of this kind, many men who muſt be acknowledged to be
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98034:12"/>Maſters of reaſon, being not able to reduce themſelves to belief, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the former method, which wanting the <hi>Divine Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> to byaſs their wills and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand aſſent, left them in deſperate Scepticiſm; for though the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of Religion are ſuch as may be preſum'd ſufficient to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, or at leaſt win aſſent; yet the <hi>medium</hi> which begets this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion is taken of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which ſaith, Reaſon in ſome ſenſe muſt be <hi>laid aſide,</hi> (which ſhall be more proved in its proper place) whilſt it reſigns it ſelf to a more inſallible conduct.</p>
            <p>Let it be alſo conſider'd, if the will and underſtanding are the Elements of Faith, that an <hi>Ethnic</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:98034:13"/>laying aſide the <hi>Divine Teſtimony</hi> and retiring to his reaſon, would be more confirm'd in his perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; As a Chymiſt aſſerts his prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and practical knowledge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove that which <hi>Theory</hi> teacheth, whilſt he Analyſes or diſſolves a body, by which he makes ſenſe a witneſs of his reaſon, and gives evidence of the truth by both: or as the Mathematical knowledge challenges greater certainty, than that in other Sciences, which taking a Scheme aſunder by demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and rebuilding it on the ſame principles, confidently and juſtly calls it true; but the ſucceſs is different in Religious caſes, as in ſome curious contexture, which is defective by its too fine threads,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98034:13"/>and not far remov'd from <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi> when moſt tenderly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woven.</p>
            <p>To this, another conſideration may be added, how it can be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined that the Heathens ſhould be ignorant of the contents of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, at leaſt, ſo far as practical, ſeeing Reaſon is allow'd a Judge naturally qualified for deciſion of Religious controverſies; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently able to comprehend matters of Faith, and in capacity to frame Religious precepts or notions without any aſſiſtance from without, <hi>but only furniſht with its own innate faculty.</hi> For that as well as he who is ſet up as judge in all controverſies muſt be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to underſtand the whole Law,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98034:14"/>though particular caſes determine the ſentence to ſome parts of it. Let this be illuſtrated by that fam'd inſtance of a Theorem revealed to <hi>Pythagoras</hi> by a Dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, which although acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to be borrowed from Revelation, yet the principles, by which judgment was paſt on it, were not derived from that <hi>kind Spirit,</hi> and it may be though poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that the Sophy might have made the diſcovery without that Monitor, and himſelf proclaim the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. This inſtance apply'd to the preſent caſe will force the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner to confeſs: that it was poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that the <hi>Ethnic</hi> might have luckily diſcover'd the matter which Religion propoſes to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98034:14"/>by his own ſaculties fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing their natural conduct, which cannot be granted.</p>
            <p>If it is objected that a great part of Religion is to be found in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens writings. It may find an anſwer from this conſideration, that no arguments taken from Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans Books for the proof of the truth of Religion, can be ſaid to prevail otherwiſe than by being probable and perſwaſive (and they borrowing their force from Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Interpretations) and thoſe which have influence on practice, notwithſtanding the ſeeming affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity between Reaſon and Religion, are like Towers or Buildings, which at a great diſtance ſeem contigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, which the eye by a nearer
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98034:15"/>approach finds remov'd from their fallacious neighborhood.</p>
            <p>That which is ſaid may find another check from the Reaſoner's fundamental poſition; which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes, that it is a ſufficient aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance to reaſon in act of faith, if the <hi>object</hi> be <hi>brought nigher</hi> by Revelation; which if true, he may impute Heatheniſh ignorance in matters of Religion, to no other cauſe but the want of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and retort the force of the former conſiderations by propoſal of this queſtion; whether it is poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that the curious and ſecret Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaniſm of nature in Animals and other Bodies, could be diſcern'd without a Microſcope, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deny'd may make it applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98034:15"/>to the former caſe? Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on being as neceſſary for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting of faith in the Heathen, as a Glaſs for diſcerning the ſmall parts of matter. This muſt not be deny'd, but if by Revelation, the bare propoſal of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is underſtood, as ſufficient to command aſſent; this will be a neceſſary conſequence, That the true Religion was not imbrac'd, or believ'd in ſeveral Ages, for no other reaſon than the <hi>Sporades</hi> (which were confuſedly diſcern'd in the <hi>Viá lacteá</hi>) were not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd till <hi>Galilaeus</hi> made the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery. For as a Teleſcope was neceſſary for the diſcerning of the one, ſo the holy Scriptures for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving of the other, the want of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98034:16"/>which cannot be thought the ſole cauſe of infidelity, the contrary being demonſtrable from the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the <hi>Jews</hi> (who muſt not altogether by one peremptory ſentence be depriv'd of their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) who have not, and perhaps could not be reduc'd to belief, though converſant with holy wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, this makes way for this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whether in the act of faith, the underſtanding is enlightned, and conſequently the will determined in ſuch manner as it cannot be by a mere natural conduct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The affirmative of this may be proved, according to the method of the Schools from this Topick of Gods concurſe with man,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98034:16"/>which alwayes leaves goodneſs as its effect, which muſt be called perfection, according to the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Character which was given of the whole Creation, that all that was made, was good, <hi>viz.</hi> Every Creature perfect in its kind, ſeeing therefore faith is the work of God on the underſtanding; 'tis paſt doubt, that it is improv'd, and the ſight more perfect.</p>
            <p>How it is perfected, ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in another diſquiſition (in this place 'tis enough, if I remove prejudices, which the former aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may create) by ſaying that the perfection which the Soul hath in the act of faith, is not ſuch as advances its nature to an Angelical degree of knowledge; yet it hath
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98034:17"/>more than could be <hi>the reſult of mere natural powers, guided by their own methods.</hi> Neither muſt this perfection be reſtrain'd to <hi>ſimple apprehenſions or notions, but complex,</hi> which would be as Ropes of Sand without any true connexion; which muſt be ſuch, becauſe matters of Religion tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend reaſons higheſt pitch, which knows not how to compound its notions or thoughts, ſo as to make true propoſitions, as may appear from an inſtance in one fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal. If this queſtion be propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to reaſon, whether God and Man could be in ſtreight an union as they are in Chriſt's perſon, it muſt remain undetermined. And God and Man muſt ſtand in the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98034:17"/>propoſition, as <hi>Subject</hi> and <hi>Praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate,</hi> till Divine teſtimony comes as a <hi>Copula.</hi> To prevent ſuch miſpriſions, this explanation may be added, <hi>viz.</hi> That by the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction attributed to the Soul in the act of faith, no new faculties are to be ſuppos'd, that could transform its nature, and remove <hi>humanity</hi> to another <hi>kind.</hi> However that which is ſaid, may make way for an objection; if the mind is thus perfected or inlightned to diſcern the truth of propoſition, of which it muſt be ignorant, whileſt guided or inform'd by its own natural evidence and conduct, all believers are Enthuſiaſts.</p>
            <p>This is no neceſſary conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of the former aſſertion:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98034:18"/>For <hi>Enthuſiaſin</hi> derives not its name from the <hi>Divine concurſe</hi> with the Soul in ſome particular acts, but when it comes at times, when it is not expected, and out of the common courſe and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, or when knowledge which ſeems extraordinary, ſuch as a man could not attain to by uſe of his reaſon; and which he doth not underſtand when ſpoken. Now the improvement of the pious mans knowledge, which is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd by regular means, which Religion commands to be us'd, deſerves not the name of <hi>Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſm.</hi> Neither can that <hi>extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary aſſiſtance</hi> promis'd to holy Councils and Synods, denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate them Enthuſiaſtick in their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98034:18"/>definitions. But I will not urge this argument, ſeeing the Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner concludes Councils no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe aſſiſted than by Reaſon, and no better qualified for finding truth than a <hi>Senate</hi> or <hi>Parliament;</hi> but further, examine the Reaſoners poſitions, which allows no more Divine aſſiſtance to Reaſon, but <hi>the near approach of the object</hi> repreſented in holy Scripture; or to ſpeak in his Metaphor, that the eye of the Soul can diſcern all ſpirituals objects, external impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments being remov'd, and brought within the <hi>Sphere</hi> of <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> This diſcerning faculty is ſuch, that the Soul can no more pretend to be furniſh't with it, than the <hi>Batt</hi> or <hi>Owl</hi> can be ſaid
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98034:19"/>to have an eye as quick and as piercing as the <hi>Eagle,</hi> and as well diſpos'd for viſion, if nature had not plac'd its proper objects at too great a diſtance. Some <hi>parts</hi> of <hi>Matter</hi> are ſo ſmall, that it is impoſſible they ſhould be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd; he deſerves to Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cled a fool, who obſerving the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries made by Microſcopes of ſmall bodies (which nature could not ſee whileſt unaſſiſted by art, and ſhe look't with her <hi>own eyes,</hi>) would attempt an invention of making diſcoveries of the parts and figures of them, of which the <hi>Air</hi> or <hi>Wind</hi> conſiſt. Some ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects are not viſible, though as near as it is poſſible they can be. Not to ſpeak much of Atoms and Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98034:19"/>points, the one not to be diſcern'd by the <hi>eye of the body,</hi> the other not diſtinctly ſeen by <hi>that of the mind,</hi> as appears from numerous Controverſies which ariſe from them, which are not ſo <hi>trivial</hi> or <hi>uſeleſs,</hi> but, that pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence can had hath made them ſubſervient (as the ſtrange <hi>Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomena's</hi> of the Load-ſtone ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted by the <hi>Reconciler</hi>) to facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the belief of the exiſtence of a <hi>ſpiritual being;</hi> by ſhewing that there are <hi>beings</hi> in nature, as well as thoſe which Religion diſcovers, whoſe exiſtence muſt be conſeſs'd, though the object are <hi>inviſible,</hi> and confound both ſenſe and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in their ſearch.</p>
            <p>This defect of natural ſight
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98034:20"/>proceeds not from the want of the <hi>near approach of the object,</hi> as is demonſtrable from the firſt proſpect Religion takes, <hi>viz. The being and nature of God</hi> (who being brought as near as imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation can wiſh or propoſe; for what object can be ſo near to the Soul, as an <hi>Idaea, which is connate</hi> with it, and inſeparable from it?) is but confuſedly diſcerned: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the <hi>ubiquity</hi> of this object implyes, it is near to every faculty which is able to diſcern it; the World alſo being as a <hi>Theater</hi> in every part of which of God is to be ſeen, yet the <hi>notions of God,</hi> which natural men frame in their brains, are as <hi>ill Repreſentations of him,</hi> as <hi>Pagans Idols,</hi> whoſe mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98034:20"/>
               <hi>Pageantry</hi> owes its begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to mans imperfect knowledg of the nature of Spirits, which is ſo far from comprehending the <hi>Supreme,</hi> that it cannot conclude the <hi>being, or underſtand the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the exiſtence of the inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, (the Angels)</hi> who are above mere humane knowledge.</p>
            <p>But if this may be retorted, by ſaying, the natural ignorance of the exiſtence and nature of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels (whoſe <hi>being,</hi> reaſon cannot neceſſary conclude) doth not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the ignorance of the Deity, whoſe exiſtence is more evident, which muſt be granted; (for as he who cannot diſcern an <hi>Atom,</hi> or the ſmalleſt viſible part of matter, may ſee a <hi>Mountain,</hi> or greater ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98034:21"/>ſo humane Reaſon ignorant of <hi>finite,</hi> may diſcern an infinite ſpirit) yet it argues the imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the ſight, for he who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſcern a <hi>Mote</hi> in a <hi>Sun-beam,</hi> cannot ſo diſtinctly diſcern the vaſt body of the <hi>Sun,</hi> and he who knows not the <hi>ratio formalis,</hi> or eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the leaſt part of matter, knows it not as it lyes in the great <hi>Bulk</hi> of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe.</hi> Let this be concluded, by ſaying, That as he who cannot diſtinctly ſee the ſmall Sands, cannot ſo diſtinctly ſee the vaſt <hi>Sea-ſhore;</hi> ſo he who knows not the nature of <hi>finite,</hi> doth not diſtinctly diſcern that of an infinite ſpirit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To what degree of knowledge, Reaſon, only following its own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98034:21"/>can lead its follower; and how he can be ſaid to be a THEIST?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Satisfaction will be given to all doubts, which can ariſe out of this inquiry, if theſe poſitions be prov'd. That Reaſon in its queſt concerning the <hi>being</hi> of God, and the manner of his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, cannot arrive to a higher pitch of certainty than that of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion. And that ſuch know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is ſo uncertain, that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be conſiſtent with that firm aſſent which Religion commands.</p>
            <p>For proof of the former, 'tis enough to direct the Reader to the precedent Diſquiſition, which ſhews how the <hi>Reaſoner</hi> puts him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the condition or quality of an <hi>Ethnick.</hi> For though Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98034:22"/>is allow'd, as neceſſary for the ſetting out his <hi>Rational guide,</hi> yet, whilſt Reaſon is ſet up Judge of reveal'd propoſitions, which muſt be ratified by appeals made to it, nothing is left of Revelation but the name, and reaſon Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated by a Heavenly Title.</p>
            <p>Theſe premis'd, will make a more eaſie digreſſion to the exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the particular method and Rules, which the Reaſoner preſcribes his guide, <hi>viz. Not to aſſent to any Concluſion, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be prov'd by natural evidence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This direction obſerv'd by the guide, will give no better aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of ſafe-conduct, than that which opinion affords, and in ſtrictneſs of Language cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>title
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98034:22"/>him to the name of <hi>Theiſt,</hi> which ſhall be more largely prov'd. But before I ſpeak to that part of this inquiry, I cannot but ſuggeſt my fear, that by this harſh concluſion I might be thought to condemn the great part of the world as <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> and to call <hi>Gods goodneſs</hi> in queſtion, in not indowing man with ſuch fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, as could diſcern the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor and trace a way to happineſs, and by this poſition to take away the ſatisfactory method of ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving doubts in Religion, <hi>viz. That there is as much evidence of the Truth of Religion, as the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of it is capable,</hi> which would be inſignificant, if Reaſon were not able to diſcern it. Theſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98034:23"/>prejudices ſhall be remov'd by the following diſcourſe; I only name them here, leaſt the Reader might think I was not ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible how many obſtacles were in the way, before I could attempt the proof of the former propoſition, and to deſire him to paſs over them, with a ſwift touch, as the Traveller tenderly goes over a <hi>Quag-mire</hi> or <hi>Quick-ſand,</hi> till he can find a more ſure bottom, to which he may be conducted by weighing the ſeveral arguments Reaſon hath for the proof of the <hi>being</hi> of a <hi>Deity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Amongſt many, let that of the <hi>French</hi> Philoſopher (who bid defiance to the <hi>Sceptick</hi>) take place, whoſe force conſiſts in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98034:23"/>theſe particular poſitions. That the <hi>Idaea</hi> of God, which is in mans mind, could not be fram'd by his invention; becauſe the Soul can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not contrive the Model of a <hi>being,</hi> which is more perfect than it ſelf. This being granted, that there is an <hi>Idaea</hi> of God in mans mind, the truth of it is prov'd from the <hi>goodneſs</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> which cannot be imagin'd to have deluded his Creature with a falſe draught of himſelf. This argument is of ſo great force, that I know none ſo cogent, if it meet with a mind praediſpos'd for the Reception of truth, but is not ſtrong enough to beat the <hi>Sceptick</hi> off his ground, becauſe the very ſinews of this argument borrow their ſtrength
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98034:24"/>from a ſuppoſition; one attribute of God being neceſſarily ſuppos'd, <hi>viz. His goodneſs,</hi> before the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner can put himſelf in a capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of arguing. However it muſt be granted, that ſuppoſition doth not deſtroy the certainty of find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing truth: for to ſuppoſe Falſity in ſome caſes, is a ſure way to find Truth; as in the <hi>Rule of falſe</hi> in Arithmetick. But this method fails in this caſe, for in thoſe Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations the ſuppoſitions are raz'd out, and laid by, when the work is perfected; but in this argument the ſuppoſition can never be laid aſide, for the truth of the Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion depends on the <hi>goodneſs</hi> of God, as known to be ſuch as would not impoſe on his Creature, which
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98034:24"/>the <hi>Sceptick</hi> will look on as but ſuppos'd. If it be urged in favour of the former argument, That Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon concludes the <hi>being</hi> or <hi>exiſtence</hi> of the Deity, and underſtands the attributes of God by rules equally certain, with thoſe in the <hi>Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical instance,</hi> ſeeing the Souls faculties are as a <hi>Standard,</hi> by which it can meaſure the Divine perfections, and find what is goodneſs or wiſdom in God by meaſuring them with the notion or footſteps of them left in the mind.</p>
            <p>The argument thus managed, muſt be acknowledged to be of great value, and ſerviceable to the caſuiſt in ſolution of doubts, but the defect of Reaſon being neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily ſupplyed with a ſuppoſition
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98034:25"/>(in this way of arguing) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which mans faculties may be ſuſpected as falſe, it is not proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the <hi>Sceptick</hi> will be perſwaded out of his affected ignorance.</p>
            <p>After this new Method let old arguments be conſider'd, which ſeem more Catholick and eaſie, being drawn from the common <hi>appearance</hi> or <hi>Phaenomena's</hi> of Nature, and obſervation of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, with thoſe from other <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picks,</hi> by which the Soul is fetter'd, ſo that it cannot evade an aſſent to the <hi>exiſtence</hi> of God; yet it will appear, that the ſtrength and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of this argument cannot command that aſſent without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of Thoughts, which implyes ignorance, and extravagancy,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98034:25"/>which are not tolerable in a Guide.</p>
            <p>That argument which is moſt obvious, is drawn from the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Fabrick of the World, which muſt be allow'd to have its due force, when it meets with a ductile mind (far remov'd from Sceptical ſtiffneſs, made ſo by a Divine diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition for receiving Truth) without which it is ſo far from conducting men to the knowledge of God, that it will rather incline the mind to Idolatry: Heathens practice is an undeniable evidence of this Truth. For it may be a reaſonable conjecture, that Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try took its riſe from the groſs conſideration of Wiſdom and Power, which appear'd in the love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98034:26"/>frame of the World, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward this power was divided and ſubdivided into ſeveral ranks of Gods and <hi>Semi-Gods.</hi> That the whole World was but as one great Idol, may appear from Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical ſayings (which Authority may paſs in this caſe, Poets being the only <hi>Divines</hi> in the Heatheniſh ages who wrapt Religion and that Secular wiſdom in verſe) who Deified the World under that great name <hi>Pan.</hi> If it be ſaid that Shepheards had this name given them by Poets, yet it is plain, that the myſtery was terminated in higher beings (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows <hi>Pan</hi> to have influence on the Oracles as Superintendent, and ſome have applyed the ſtory of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98034:26"/>his death to Chriſt's ſuffering) which is enough to ſhew he was more than a Shepherd, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. For that age, as others before, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd the World and its Creator in one groſſe notion which they expres't by <hi>Pan,</hi> as may be prov'd from the account which <hi>Orpheus</hi> gives of that Idoliz'd name in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother place further to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd: But ſeeing this way of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument from Practice, may not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ſo convincing as that of The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory, becauſe all do not tread the ſame ſteps with equal ſucceſs, and the queſtion is not, what know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God hath been, but what may be learn't from the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>To this demand a ſhort anſwer
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:98034:27"/>may be return'd. When a man takes a ſerious proſpect of the World, one of theſe thoughts will ariſe, either that it had a beginning of it ſelf, or that it was the work of ſome Architect: if he is inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to allow the former, all that Reaſon can do in order to his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, is, to ſhew the impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the World's being its own cauſe or maker. This prov'd, can only remove him from Atheiſm, or at leaſt diſpoſe him for a belief of the exiſtence and knowledge of God. He therefore who ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rives to this degree of knowledg in ſtrictneſs and propriety of ſpeech, deſerves not the name <hi>Theiſt,</hi> any more than a man come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of a Cell or Wilderneſs,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:98034:27"/>ſeeing a Diamond or Jewel, hath only ſo much knowledg to paſs ſentence, that it is not of the ſame kind of ſtones which he treads on, deſerves the name of a <hi>Jeweller,</hi> or ſeeing a ſtately Pallace, hath on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly skill to conclude, that the ſtones did not meet by mutual conſent (as the fabulous ſtory ſayes of the building of <hi>Thebes</hi> for erecting that Fabrick, neither did grow ſo uniformly out of the Earth), may be ſaid to know an <hi>Architect</hi> or a Builder.</p>
            <p>If in defence of this argument it is ſaid, that he who denyes that a Fabrick can raiſe it ſelf, tacitly implyes the neceſſity of the <hi>being</hi> of ſome <hi>Builder.</hi> This granted, will not relieve the Idiot, for the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:98034:28"/>Builder can be no otherwiſe ſaid to be known by him, than under the general notion of a <hi>Cauſe.</hi> Now who will be ſo ridiculous as to ſay, that a man underſtands what an <hi>Architect</hi> is, and what kind and degree of knowledge gives him that name, who hath only a general notion of him, by which he calls him the <hi>cauſe of a Houſe,</hi> which deſcription is ſo rude, that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be allow'd, except Logick can juſtifie it by terms of Art unknown to the Idiot, however it cannot acquit him from the imputation of groſſe ignorance, which will appear greater when he conſiders the nice operations of nature. For if Creatures are look't upon which are moſt expos'd to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:98034:28"/>view, nature ſitting in them as on the ſtage, it is but little (and that conjectural) knowledge, he can pretend to; let the Heavenly bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies be an inſtance to prove mans ignorance of their nature and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence; who will pretend to know (except from Aſtrologer as ignorant as bold) for what deſign the Heavens ſo regularly muſter their forces, till the event ſhews it, or to determine what dependance the World hath on ſome of the Stars, and poſitively conclude, that they are not Worlds; though not of the ſame frame with this, of which Men are Inhabitants? Now if man is ignorant of the dependance of one part of the Creation or another (as he muſt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:98034:29"/>be except nature were ſupplyed with greater aſſiſtance than that of <hi>Teleſcopes,</hi> or of any device which invention hath yet found) his knowledg muſt be ſaid to be ſo imperfect, that it is not probable the argument drawn from the Worlds Harmony, ſhould be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent, when it meets with ſo much ignorance. To ſpeak all; the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and uncertain knowledg of natures works, rather diſpoſeth man for admiration, than full ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of all doubts. But that I may not ſeem to detract from humanity, ſuppoſe the harmoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſubordination of cauſes was underſtood, this only implies, that there is a power which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrains them from deſtroying or
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:98034:29"/>
               <hi>falling foul</hi> one on the other, or makes them ſubſervient to ſome end, of which the Reaſoner is and muſt be ignorant.</p>
            <p>If this aſſertion ſeem too rigid, which ſuppoſes man in the World as in Cimmercan darkneſs, let it be granted that the mere <hi>Reaſoner</hi> hath a partial knowledg of God, if he will be content with the name of a partial <hi>Theiſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let it be alſo conſider'd, that it is poſſible, that the ſame contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance may ſeem harmonious to one, and appear not to be ſo to another. The Inhabitants of the <hi>Northern Climates</hi> may admire and adore the Sun for its warm in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, whilſt thoſe between the <hi>Tropicks</hi> breath imprecations, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:98034:30"/>it ſcorches by more direct rays. Let more be granted by ſaying that the Fabrick of the world is ſuch (if underſtood) that it muſt be concluded to be a <hi>Divine work;</hi> yet ſeeing there is a poſſibility that matter and moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (as the <hi>French</hi> Philoſophy teacheth) might work it ſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that order which is to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir'd in the world, the natural Reaſoner will have little ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to his doubts from the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the worlds Harmony; eſpecially ſeeing the <hi>French</hi> Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis is conſiſtent with it ſelf, and ſolveth doubts on its own principles, which will abate the force of the uſual arguments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Chance</hi> and the <hi>Epicurean
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:98034:30"/>Philoſophy.</hi> It alſo appears that ſome have been ſenſible of the weakneſs of an argument drawn from this <hi>Topick of Harmony,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proving Gods exiſtence from the groſs conſideration of <hi>matter mov'd,</hi> than as it is modeliz'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to forms. This way of arguing ſeems to preſs the concluſion with greater neceſſity than the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but nearly lookt into can make a man no more a <hi>Theiſt,</hi> than the <hi>Idiot</hi> in the former inſtance. The examination of this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment might end by the citation of a Poetical ſaying, cited by St. <hi>Paul. By him we live, we move and have our being,</hi> (which motion (I preſume) intended to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:98034:31"/>to the motion of the parts of mans body) is equally, if not more valid to prove the exiſtence of God, than that argument which is drawn from a more diſtant <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pick, viz. The firſt impreſs on mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before I paſs to another na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural evidence of the <hi>being of God,</hi> I cannot but confeſs that the harmonious Fabrick of the world is us'd in holy Scripture, and by the antient Fathers, as a confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their doctrine and faith, which might be examin'd and confirm'd by ſuch contemplation; yet I preſume I ſhall not be injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to <hi>Scripture</hi> or <hi>Fathers,</hi> if I ſay, that Method was us'd, becauſe it is more univerſal and agreeable
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:98034:31"/>to imagination and common rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, than other arguments which are more artificial; not that it was thought to be more cogent. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, it is an eaſie conjecture, which ſuppoſes that ſuch arguments were intended for believers, or at leaſt thoſe who were diſpos'd to entertain their Doctrine, not for ſceptical Reaſoners. If it be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther urged that the holy Fathers have made Converts and confuted Atheiſm by this method; yet it is not ſure to find ſucceſs with all perſons, eſpecially ſuch <hi>Reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> as allow nothing to be certain which cannot recommend it ſelf with an undoubted evidence, or impoſſibility of being otherwiſe. Suppoſe this pertinent queſtion
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:98034:32"/>was propos'd to the Atheiſtical Reaſoner. If a man ſhould find a Statue or an Altar with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, whether he would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude it was poſſible ſome liquid ſubſtance (like <hi>Aqua fortis</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roding Iron) might caſually ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect that which art ſhould do, and by the ſame reaſon preſs't to give his anſwer, determining whether the World wrought it ſelf into its lovely frame. If the affirmative is anſwer'd, 'tis true that his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion is enough to denominate him a <hi>Mad-man,</hi> but he will not value or think himſelf injur'd by ſuch compellations who ſceptical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſputes; for he will be ſo bold as to ſay that as Religion and true Faith was once preſerved by one
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:98034:32"/>
               <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> ſo may truth be found only in one ſingle perſon.</p>
            <p>To give the Reaſoner a fair tryal of his knowledge, let the former inſtance be reveiw'd with a larger conceſſion, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Idiot who acknowledgeth the building to have ſome cauſe (though the manner of expreſſion is rude) yet implyes the <hi>being</hi> of a builder, as the ſaying, the world was not its own cauſe, doth aſſert the <hi>exiſtence</hi> of God. This being granted his ignorance will appear, for it is poſſible and commonly obſerv'd, that men may ſpeak ſentences and not underſtand what they imply, or what may be inferr'd from them. How many ſayings which fall ſuddenly from ſome perſon,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:98034:33"/>whoſe ſenſe being meaſur'd by the bare interpretation of the words, is but trivial or ordinary, but by deduction will bear a higher mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; whence it muſt be infer'd, that thoſe concluſions which are gather'd as conſequences of the words (which ſeem'd not to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port ſo much) cannot be proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call'd his, who ſpake the words, but muſt be own'd by him who advanced them to a higher ſenſe. Idiots ſometimes are like Oracles and Prophets, whoſe high effuſions are not underſtood by thoſe who ſpeak, ſuch are the ſentences of ſome Philoſophers and Poetical Raptures, which according to the Authors words or ſenſe ſavour'd of a low and mean degree of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:98034:33"/>till ſome Chriſtians reading their Books Conſecrated them by Comments and Concluſions, of which they could never have thought. Hence it is, that the Books of ſome ancient Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher are now like the fam'd Ship, which was ſo oft repair'd, till no old Plank remain'd. Many wiſe Concluſions appear in Heatheniſh writings, but are as myſterious <hi>Characters</hi> and <hi>Cyphers,</hi> which only the Religious by comparing them with Revelation can under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand. Theſe <hi>Effata,</hi> or ſayings, are like ſigns which Deaf and dumb men make, who neither have advantage of nature to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand or ſpeak, whoſe Interpreters are as <hi>Mouths</hi> and <hi>underſtanding</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:98034:34"/>too, whilſt they ſtretch their Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations, beyond that which the <hi>Significators</hi> deſign'd, or could declare. Hence it appears, that the Reaſoner in this particular queſt (whilſt he utters divine ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences not underſtood by himſelf, but to be Conſecrated by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentator,) may not be put in the Catalogue of <hi>Theiſts,</hi> except it can be imagin'd, <hi>implicit Reaſon,</hi> may be allow'd as much as <hi>implicit Faith.</hi> Hitherto it being conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd what degree of knowledge may be acquir'd by the Idiot (for in this Queſt the Reaſoner muſt be content to be ſo called) from the contemplation of the world, let a man of another apprehenſion (whoſe knowledg is more reſin'd
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:98034:34"/>by induſtry and art) who appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> groſsly conceiv'd by the Idiot, as an <hi>Architect,</hi> be Catechiz'd in this Article of his <hi>natural faith,</hi> he will be found ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant. For although the world is a great Glaſs, in which its <hi>Maker</hi> may be ſeen; yet the Lineaments are ſo ſcatter'd and confus'd, that it is almoſt impoſſible to reduce them to a perfect form, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear from the conſideration of the method us'd for the proof and knowledge of God, from a proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of the world, which takes all the perfections which lie ſcatter'd in the Creatures, and then imagins them to be in one moſt perfect Being, (which implyes a denyal of all imperfections) and all thoſe
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:98034:35"/>concentred in that Being, are <hi>modo infinito,</hi> as the Schools ſay. This argument bids fair for the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, but will fail, when ſtrictly examin'd. For though it is gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that the perfections which are in the Creatures, are the ſame, though in an inferiour degree, with thoſe attributed to the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, yet the ignorance of the manner how they are in this <hi>Being,</hi> which is infinite, and conſequently incomprehenſible, will make him ſo far fall ſhort of his deſign'd knowledg (attempting vainly to meaſure Infinity by his finite Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures) that he deſerves no more to be called a <hi>Theiſt,</hi> than a man, who hath only ſeen the Suns image in a drop, &amp; as it is in every part of the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:98034:35"/>Rainbow, or the Stars in a Pool, can own the name of an Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. This method is as inſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant, as addition of numbers to numbers; ſo that is impoſſible that they can have any <hi>denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> or as an attempt to meaſure two quantities (one by the other) which in their own nature are <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commenſurable,</hi> or without any known proportion. By theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances I give greater advantage to the cavilling Adverſary, than he could reaſonably expect, for there is greater diſproportion between God and his Creatures, than can be between <hi>quantity</hi> and <hi>quantity,</hi> However let it not be thought an unneceſſary crowding in inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, if it be ſaid, this method is ſo
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:98034:36"/>far from being infallible, that it falls ſhort of the certainty of operations in <hi>Decimals,</hi> which are not true, if examin'd by Rules of Demonſtration, yet ſerve in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, and the Error is not to be diſcern'd. But he who attempts to know God by this way of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning, will fail in practice as much as <hi>Thcory.</hi> The Heathens, who fram'd a notion of God by this method, and ſuited their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals to it, were ſo notoriouſly er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous, that ſome of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts and Concluſions are not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concileable with Religious truth.</p>
            <p>Another branch of the Reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners argument, is the ſubordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Cauſes, which in this Queſt need not be diſtinguiſhed
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:98034:36"/>nicely from Harmony, one being the reſult of the other, both of which are ſo far from being Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick arguments, which may convince all, that there are ſcarce any, who are able to paſs judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on that Harmonious ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: for he who is a fit judg of the Harmony of the world, muſt be ſuppos'd to know all the parts of it and their uſe, or how they have dependance one on the other, as <hi>Cauſes and Effects.</hi> How im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect this knowledg is, will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear from a view of natural Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, in which moſt of the diſcoveries are but conjectures, though called Demonſtrations. I do not deſign to ſtart many old Errors, it will be ſufficient to ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:98034:37"/>this conſideration. That the ancient Sophies who took this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod to conduct them, had an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect proſpect of the World's Harmony, as may be concluded from the Aſtronomy (which is converſant about the moſt glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and harmonious part of the World) extant in their ages, the beſt and moſt valuable part of which was compriz'd in the ſam'd <hi>Almageſt.</hi> Now how monſtrous and defective a <hi>Ptolomaic Syſtem</hi> is, is plain from late obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. But omitting theſe, let it be conſider'd, as ſuiting with that age in which (ſome diſcoveries (which deſtroy it) were not made; yet it will appear to be, if compar'd with the <hi>Copernican,</hi> as
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:98034:37"/>an ill contriv'd Engine which moves with many Wheels, <hi>Cycles</hi> and <hi>Epicycles,</hi> when one or few would make it more perfect. This perhaps may be the reaſon of that ſaying faſtned on <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> who conſidering the world's Fabrick in <hi>Ptolomie</hi>'s <hi>Sphere,</hi> raſhly ſaid, that he could contrive the world in a better frame, had he power to Create. Here I may expect a Check from the Reaſoner, who may demand, whether I thought any late, or more Harmonious Syſtem might more effectually improve this argument? To this queſtion I only ſay, that late inventions may improve the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by rendring it more preſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, not much more demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:98034:38"/>For Harmony is a certain proportion between numbers or magnitudes, which is not called ſo only for this reaſon, that ſome quantities have a <hi>mutual alliance, and agree in ſome third, which is common to both;</hi> but as it hath reſpect to the mind which appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends them; as Muſick is ſo called, becauſe it kindly complies with the ear. 'Tis confeſs'd, that ſo much may be concluded from this Topick, that the humane Soul and the world ows their original (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the approbation which Reaſon gives concerning the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable contrivance of the worlds Fabrick) to the ſame <hi>Being</hi> or <hi>Cauſe;</hi> but as to the nature of that cauſe, a man can conclude nothing,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:98034:38"/>much more diſtinctly and certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, than the Idiot in the former inſtance.</p>
            <p>The next natural evidence of the exiſtence of God, is from the general conſent of all Nations, of which none ſo barbarous as not to own it, (as it was well obſerved by that great Oratour, who did not much improve it for his own information, as appears from his Books) yet this argument will find more Barbariſm in the Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Reaſoner of this age, than the former was guilty of; For this knowledg of God as it is general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly found, is not prov'd by the Reaſoners method, which unravels and analyſes all by reaſon before it is believ'd, but is rather a <hi>common
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:98034:39"/>notion,</hi> or <hi>natural impreſs,</hi> which is on the loweſt degree of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, <hi>that there is a Being, able to Reward or Puniſh;</hi> yet this is not the concluſion of the diſcurſive facultie; for thoſe who cannot prove a God, give aſſent to this Concluſion of his exiſtence; which proof conſider'd, though in the groſs notion of an Idiot is more valid, than the Reaſoners argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments modeliz'd into Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſms, and is more agreeable to the account, Revelation gives of God, which only expreſſes his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence, when he deſcribes himſelf, by ſaying <hi>I am.</hi> Hence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, that the natural knowledg of God, ſo diffus'd over the whole VVorld, is like that of an Idiot,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:98034:39"/>who ſeeing a Circle can confeſs it to be ſo, although he cannot prove it by tryal, whether each ray or line drawn from the Center to the Circumference is equal.</p>
            <p>This argument thus managed, will not find any ſucceſs with the Reaſoner, whoſe Rules oblige him to admit nothing as true (though the will is ſo inclinable to aſſent, that it can be ſooner confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded than diverted) except it have paſs'd the exact Inquiſition of the underſtanding by diſcourſe. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, he may ſuppoſe or doubt, whether that general conſent was the reſult of natural knowledg, or the Doctrine of ſome wiſe men, whoſe open profeſſion of that truth occaſioned the vulgar (in
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:98034:40"/>proceſs of ſeveral ages) to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude it natural knowledg. Theſe thoughts in the Reaſoner can be look't upon no otherwiſe than a mere cavil, he being not able to ſhew, <hi>how, when</hi> or <hi>where</hi> this notion was fram'd (as it well obſerv'd by a late Author) yet the ſuggeſtion will not ſhake the ſceptical mind, for he who will be ſo bold to conclude the whole Worlds Repreſentatives in a Council may err, will not boggle in ſaying, the general conſent of all Nations might be terminated in an Error.</p>
            <p>Thus far the World hath been conſider'd, as to its Harmony of parts, from which 't will be an ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie digreſſion to the Harmonious
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:98034:40"/>diſpoſition of mans mind, which inclines him to a civil life. From this Topick no weak arguments are drawn for the proof of the <hi>exiſtence</hi> of God, ſeeing mans re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, becauſe civiliz'd, life is as great a wonder in Policy, as the ſubordination of cauſes in nature, which prevents mutinies amongſt the Elements, and hinders mutual deſtruction. Now this bond of civil Society borrowes its ſtrength from the ſupream Law-giver, who by his Divine Empire in mans mind, diſpoſeth it, for mutual agreement with equals, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to Superiours. This ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument muſt have its allowance of validity, but it muſt be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, that this, as the former,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:98034:41"/>wants its due force, except the exiſtence of God is ſuppos'd, which the ſtrict Reaſoner will have prov'd, before he will own him, or any deductions which depend on it, For as it is confeſs'd, that the diſtinction of <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Evil</hi> is the foundation of humane Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; ſo it muſt be allow'd, that actions are no otherwiſe called <hi>Good</hi> or <hi>Evil,</hi> but as they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the natural Conſcience, which ſuppoſeth the exiſtence of God. Hence the defect of the argument appears, ſeeing he who proves God's <hi>exiſtence</hi> by this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, neceſſarily ſuppoſeth a <hi>being,</hi> which endow'd his mind with ſuch knowledg, which could point out <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Evil.</hi> Seeing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:98034:41"/>the truth of Concluſions drawn by this method, depends on a ſuppoſal of the exiſtence of that <hi>being</hi> which ſhould be prov'd, it cannot be imagined to have much force to convince the Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, for he ſuppoſition makes him retire to his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the whole argument as weak <hi>Suppoſitions</hi> and Hypotheſes; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing like flaccid Nerves, which want ſpirits to fortifie them, only ſerving to knit Paralytical mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers together, but without ſtrength. If it is ſaid that ſome Heathens, who had little or no knowledg of God, or at leaſt own'd a falſe Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which is aequivalent to none, did many Heroical and good Acts, which implies the notion of <hi>good</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:98034:42"/>and <hi>Evil.</hi> This may be granted, yet their actions could no further be called <hi>Good</hi> or <hi>Evil</hi> than they had reſpect to a Deity, of which they had only a confus'd notion. For the conformity of an action with the Law of nature (which is a <hi>Divine impreſs</hi> on the mind) makes it to be good, being the <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal reaſon</hi> of it, as the diſconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity makes it vitious. Hence it follows, that thoſe actions which were good, were not known to be ſo, but as they were meaſur'd by the <hi>goodneſs</hi> of God, which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies the former ſuppoſition.</p>
            <p>Then next part of this Diſquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall be the examination of the force of that argument which is drawn from terrours of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:98034:42"/>upon Evil committed, which is of ſo great force (with a due allowance of Heavenly aſſiſtance, Grace and Revelation) that it ſtorms the Atheiſt's ſtrongeſt holds, and ſo beats him off his ground, that he knows not where to ſecure himſelf, but without, it is as little forcible as thoſe drawn from other Topicks. For it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing prov'd, that no action can be ſaid to be <hi>Good</hi> or <hi>Evil,</hi> but as it hath relation to the <hi>Divine Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>Will,</hi> either as it is written in mans mind in the natural frame of his Soul, or by external con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance by revelation; it is a praepoſterous proof from that To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pick of fear, that God puniſheth <hi>Evil,</hi> before it is granted (which
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:98034:43"/>cannot be) that reaſon knows what is <hi>Evil,</hi> without the Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of a Deity, without which, fear is ſo far from being a <hi>Medium</hi> to help the Reaſoner in his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions, that it is more probable to hinder him in his natural Queſt. That which leads men to certainty, according to the Reaſoners me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, muſt inform the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and conſequently determine the will after ſuch a free manner as muſt exclude compulſion, but fear or any argument taken from it (which cannot be ſo fram'd, but that paſſion will interpoſe it ſelf) is ſo far from doing either, that it cannot determine the will without ſome kind of violence done to it, ſo he that acts out of fear, cannot ſo
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:98034:43"/>properly be ſaid to be a <hi>free Agent.</hi> Neither is it leſs prejudicial to the underſtanding, caſting a miſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the eye of the mind by its turbulency; The Philoſopher was ſenſible of this, who concluded its removal neceſſary from the mind in the ſearch of Truth. <hi>Si vis lumine claro cernere verum, gaudia pelle, pelle timorem. Boet. de Conſol. Phil.</hi> Fear is plac't in the Soul as tempeſts in the <hi>loweſt Region,</hi> through which it is as dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult for the mind to have a free and clear proſpect, as for the Sun to diſcover its luſtre through a Cloud. Let it not be argued from Holy Scripture, that ſear was a neceſſary introduction to the knowledg of God, as appears
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:98034:44"/>from the apprehenſion the People had of wonders on <hi>Mount-Sinai,</hi> and the <hi>Moſaical appeal</hi> to them, if ever they ſaw ſuch aſtoniſhing wonders. This tends not ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly to juſtifie the former argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: for it may be reaſonably pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd, that this method was us'd rather to confirm them in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of a Deity before entertain'd, and to prevent Apoſtacy, than to be their firſt Tutor, to inſtruct them in the firſt Article of the <hi>Jewiſh,</hi> as well as <hi>Chriſtian Creed.</hi> The moſt direct way to wiſdom, as it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects ſpeculation, is not by fear excited in the mind, although it hath great influence on practice, as the ſenſe of that holy ſaying imports, which calls <hi>the fear of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:98034:44"/>God the beginning of wiſdom,</hi> for in that ſentence, the <hi>exiſtence</hi> of God is ſuppos'd, before fear takes its place in order to inſtruction. However it was a neceſſary defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſative againſt Idolatry, to which the Jews were too inclinable. In ſuch particular caſes, ſuch turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent paſſions may uſher in Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but generally conſider'd, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confound than inform the mind. For it ſeems not deſign'd for the Chriſtian, but that part of the world which may be call'd the Devil's Province, in which he is ador'd by numerous votaries, led to that adoration by fear, which gives occaſion of conſidering, how that turbulent paſſion rather diſpoſeth man for Diabolical wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:98034:45"/>than that of the true God. For ſeeing the Devils can inflict puniſhments, or rather vex men with Tortures which excite ſear, they may poſſibly terminate mans Devotion in them as Deities. If it is ſaid that this aſſertion implies impoſſibilities, whilſt a power is allow'd to the Devil of terrifying the Conſcience with puniſhment, which the Reaſoner may conclude Eternal, as well as Temporal. A ſhort reply will ſhew, that this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection cannot be the ſenſe of a man in his pure naturals, except he was aſſur'd of the immortality of his Soul, of which ſome Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens ſpake doubtfully, though they confidently preſum'd its eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal duration, becauſe they could
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:98034:45"/>not imagine, how it ſhould periſh by any known cauſes. Therefore their <hi>all-natural Divinity</hi> did not conclude eternal Rewards, or Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, ſuitable to the Souls du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. 'Tis true Hell is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſo ſhadow'd by the Poets, as if their Poems had borrow'd from Revelation, but their Poetical concluſions in this caſe can be no further credited, than they ſpeak of the Souls immortality, of which there is as little ſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily ſaid, as in <hi>Proſe;</hi> beſides they being the reſult of fancy, cannot effectually commend themſelves as matters of <hi>natural faith:</hi> For if the Authors of ſuch Poetical ſentences, could they be imagin'd to riſe again, and take a view of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:98034:46"/>the Concluſions of <hi>Mythologiſts,</hi> and thoſe who write Comments on their Poems. I might reaſonably doubt, whether ſeveral opinions faſtned on them by deduction would be own'd as their genuine ſenſe. I need not add this, that ſome have openly declar'd in <hi>verſe</hi> as much as others in <hi>Proſe,</hi> that they were fabulous fictions, not much to be regarded by minds, not too much byaſs'd by paſſion, or ſuperſtitious fear. For not only the profane and Atheiſtical Poet concluded the future ſtate as dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſaying, <hi>Quid Styga, Quid Bara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrum, Quid nomina vana timetis?</hi> but others, whoſe invention and fancy were more ſoberly bounded, and free from the extravagancy of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:98034:46"/>more <hi>dangerous Raptures.</hi> Before I take one ſtep further in this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition, 'tis neceſſary, that an objection be remov'd, which may render what is ſaid leſs credible, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Devil hath no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of himſelf, neither can act any thing by his own abſolute Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, but by Deputation, and it cannot be imagin'd, that he ſhould puniſh ſin with eternal puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſeeing he is a finite Creature, and his buſineſs is to promote it. To the firſt part of this objection, the ſame anſwer muſt be return'd, which was given to the former. That it is ſuch as the mere <hi>Reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> cannot ſtart, for Revelation only informs man of the nature of Devils, and the limitation of their
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:98034:47"/>power, wherefore ſeeing reaſon could not ſuggeſt, that it is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently anſwer'd by ſhewing it is impertinent; the other part of it, which threatens the former aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, cannot deſtroy it; for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Devil cannot be thought inclinable to puniſh <hi>ſin</hi> properly ſo call'd, yet practice ſhews, that he Tortures ſome as ſinners againſt his Laws, by which he ſupports his Dominion in the World, which offenders deſerve the name of actors of good, as by avoiding vice (according to the plain definition of vertue, <hi>virtus eſt vitium fugere</hi>) men become vertuous. The <hi>Indian</hi> concludes he that offended the ſupream power, though but Diabolical,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:98034:47"/>when miſchief, or any extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary appearance, threatens his ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine. Hence appears the poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of terminating Devotion in a <hi>finite being,</hi> for it being repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as dreadful, as any deduction from mere reaſon can make it, 'tis no great wonder if a man look on that power, as infinite (which is not ſo) ſeeing it bounds his thoughts, if not tranſcends all he can imagine, and conſequently adore that power, as a God or the <hi>ſupream Being,</hi> which is only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted, and limited. This may be further prov'd from <hi>Sacred ſtory,</hi> which ſayes, the ignorant mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude declar'd the Apoſtles Gods in <hi>humane ſhape,</hi> and were hardly reſtrain'd from an Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:98034:48"/>Worſhip. This inſtance is a ſufficient evidence of the truth of the former aſſertion, although it ſeems to fail, becauſe of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between <hi>good Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>bad Angels;</hi> yet both agree in this, that they are Creatures, which ſhews it is poſſible, that <hi>finite beings</hi> may be miſtaken for God. For this inſtance juſtifying the poſſibility of adoration given to <hi>finite beings,</hi> and the inclination of men who are too ready to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip them, when they ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves able to do good in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degree (ſuch as was wrought by the Apoſtles Miracles). It may be concluded by the ſame reaſon, that when <hi>any Being</hi> manifeſts it ſelf with ſuch power, which is able
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:98034:48"/>to inflict the greateſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the <hi>Reaſoner</hi> may own it as God.</p>
            <p>Before more is ſaid to prove the former poſition, 'tis neceſſary, that ſome objections be remov'd, one of which may ariſe out of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, which ſaid the ignorant multitude in that caſe were not to be eſteemed as rational men, being without the due uſe of their reaſon, which could inform them of the impoſſibility of finite Creatures being Metamorphiz'd to a Deity, or the perfections of it to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to a Creature. To this a double anſwer muſt be given ſuitable to the parts of the objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to the firſt of which it may be ſaid, if the ignorant votaries were
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:98034:49"/>ſo much aſtoniſh'd with the Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles that <hi>ſurpriz'd reaſon</hi> knew not how to act; and thoſe which have been conducted by this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument drawn from fear, which confounds the underſtanding, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear with ſuch confus'd zeal, which ſavours more of diſtraction than ſobriety of mind, (as it is evident from the Indians pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice,) it may be concluded that the Topick from which they argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Emergencies</hi> of ſome <hi>extraordinary power</hi> put them in that confuſion. To the ſecond, 'tis enough to ſay, that it is not neceſſary, that it ſhould be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in this caſe, whether the Daemons terrifying that part of the World with malicious prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:98034:49"/>are <hi>finite,</hi> or <hi>infinite</hi> with a real reſpect to their natures, but the underſtanding, which makes <hi>eſse &amp; apparere,</hi> ſignifie the ſame in matters of <hi>natural faith.</hi> This may be further confirm'd from Heathens practice, who ador'd Oracles, which were <hi>Devils Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> in ſome parts of the World, but worſhipped as the <hi>ſupreme powers.</hi> But perhaps it may be ſaid, that the Heathen eſteem'd the Oracles only as <hi>Secretaries or mouths</hi> of the Deity as the Etymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and Sibylla implies, yet practice did not make this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, for Monarchs, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted them, thought they had taken Advice or Counſel from the <hi>ſupreme power</hi> (which was only
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:98034:50"/>diſtinguiſhed by the names of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral places where their ſentences were utter'd) which <hi>Supremacy</hi> was boldly written on their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, till by Chriſt's coming the glory was buried, and the <hi>proud inſcription</hi> chang'd to an <hi>Epitaph,</hi> the Oracle being <hi>ſpiritually dead,</hi> in that forc't return to Hell, which occaſion'd this ſad com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint to a Votary, who came to conſult of future events.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Me puer Hebraeus divos Deus ipſe gubernans</l>
               <l>Cedere ſede jubet triſtemq, redire ſub Orcum.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The Oracles were neceſſitated to make ſuch confeſſions, it being one part of their pennance to proclaim their own weakneſs, and neceſſary ſubjection to that <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Being,</hi> of whom they ſo
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:98034:50"/>prophetically ſpake, as if they had been the <hi>Oracles</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> as appears by the anſwer given by <hi>Apollo</hi>'s Oracle, to one demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what God was
<q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Who could imagine that the Devil was the Authour of this almoſt ſacred verſe, were it not conſider'd that God layes a neceſſity on the evil Angels, that they ſhall proclaim his power, for the Devils in the <hi>Caves</hi> and <hi>Groves,</hi> as well as thoſe amongſt the <hi>Tombs</hi> did ſpeak truth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Chriſt, though it added to their Torment? This is enough to demonſtrate, that thoſe true
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:98034:51"/>ſayings when ſpoken by them were extorted, and they (as much as ſpiritual beings are capable of) put on the <hi>rack</hi> by ſuch confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. This <hi>Oracular cunning</hi> (which would not confeſs Chriſt but when forc't) occaſions a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark on the Devils ſubtilty, who being neceſſitated to acknowledg him, inſinuates this to his Votaries that Oracles are God's <hi>Nuncio</hi>'s, and ally'd to a <hi>Deity</hi> as <hi>Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors,</hi> whilſt the <hi>lye</hi> is <hi>minc't</hi> by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. If the Reaſoner take advantage from this citation of refuting the former poſition, by ſaying that they ſeem'd not to aim at adoration <hi>as infinite beings;</hi> neither were they eſteem'd by wiſe men as any other than <hi>Angels,</hi> as
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:98034:51"/>appears from Heathen compellati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which ſpeak them <hi>Miniſters;</hi> beſide the Oracles more plain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, who would have prayer directed to him in this language <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Yet it muſt be obſerv'd, though the Devil calls himſelf <hi>Daemon</hi> or <hi>Angel,</hi> yet he calls himſelf <hi>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſcient</hi> and owns <hi>univerſal wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> which cannot be allow'd any Creature, and ſeeing he injoyns a <hi>form of Prayer</hi> to be directed to him; he tacitly inſinuates to his Votaries that he is God, for he to whom Prayers are made muſt be God according to Heathens Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which owns no invocations of Creatures as <hi>Mediators.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let it be granted that the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:98034:52"/>Oracles were <hi>Angels,</hi> and only <hi>Jupiter, Apollo,</hi> which ſome other were ador'd as Deities, this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion will be ſo far from deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the former poſition, that it ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confirms it, by allowing ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to <hi>finite beings,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi> and <hi>Apollo,</hi> and many other who muſt be in the Catalogue of men, who made uſe of Dreams and Oracles to promote their <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theoſis</hi> as <hi>Lactant. cap.</hi> 8. <hi>De ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine erroris,</hi> argues, <hi>Eos ipſos quos docuimus Deos non eſſe, Majeſtatem ſuam oſtendiſse prodigijs, inſomniis, auguriis &amp; Oraculis,</hi> &amp;c. More might be cited out of that Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as pertinent, the deſign of which (as well as of this Tract) being to ſhew the uſe of Reaſon in
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:98034:52"/>Religion, and how much the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural man is guilty of folly, who intirely reſigns himſelf to its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct; but I am ſenſible that I muſt appear tedious in this firſt Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition, and inexcuſable too, did not the Subject treated off exact the moſt ſtrict examination, and ſtarting all that can be ſaid againſt the former poſition. Wherefore let the Reaſoner object in another way of Heathens practice, in ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they did not always ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate their Devotions in that <hi>Being</hi> in which they found a <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimen</hi> of <hi>Divine power</hi> or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, which may be prov'd from the <hi>Sibylls,</hi> who appear'd no leſs Divine than the <hi>Oracles;</hi> yet were ſo far from being ador'd,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:98034:53"/>that they ſcarce found civil Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment from the greateſt <hi>Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages</hi> in the World; to this obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction I will only ſuggeſt theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations as an anſwer. That the diſregard and little eſtimation they had in the World proceeded from the different manner and matter of predictions of the Sibylls and Oracles, the former were to come to paſs after many Revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Years and Ages, the latter as <hi>ex tempore Prophets</hi> ſpake to every particular queſtion, and their mouths open to each Votary. Now ſeeing the Sibylls propheſies were to be fulfilled not untill ſome ages were paſt, it may be eaſily imagin'd that active minds would be more prone to adore the Oracles
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:98034:53"/>who were as <hi>Tutelar Angels</hi> to adviſe in every particular caſe, than thoſe who ſpake more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally of what ſhould come to paſs at further diſtance. Another rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may be given why the Sibylls were not ador'd; becauſe their Birth and Linage was but humane, it was not probable they ſhould purchaſe Adoration, for the <hi>known humanity</hi> was an obſtacle which hinder'd worſhip due to <hi>him,</hi> to whom all Oracles and Angels ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit with fear of that <hi>power</hi> which was able to ſilence them. If it is ſaid, that this anſwer cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the objection, for the ſame reaſon will deſtroy Heatheniſh Devotion to <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and other reputed Deities, who were only
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:98034:54"/>
               <hi>men Deifi'd</hi> by opinion of ſome fond Votaries; It muſt be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd, that they were eſteem'd as eternal, though really they were mortalls; which opinion was enough to denominate them Gods; for in Heathens devotion <hi>to be,</hi> and to <hi>be believ'd</hi> to be ſo, was the ſame. As <hi>Alexander</hi> thought it was enough to his purpoſe, that the Barbarians were perſwaded he was a <hi>God,</hi> though he knew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be but mortal, as he glories in the deluſion; whilſt he ſays, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The Idiots conquerd themſelves by their falſe zeal and perſwaſions: ſo it anſwers diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical deſigns, if Devils are miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for Gods. Beſides the Sibylls
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:98034:54"/>were ſo much like <hi>Apoſtl's,</hi> that they did not pretend to Worſhip, due to them, but another, of whom they Propheſied; neither did they, as the <hi>Deviliſh Oracles,</hi> require any form of Worſhip or Prayer to be directed to them; it was as much as they aim'd at, if they were thought (according to the Etymology of their name <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) to be of the Heavenly Counſel. If that age had been ſo zealouſly inclin'd to adore their wiſdom, and could be imagin'd to have conſider'd their Propheſies as fulfilled; yet the matter of what was foretold, would convince the World that they were not <hi>Gods,</hi> nor claim'd Adoration. Theſe circumſtances conſider'd will give ſatisfaction to
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:98034:55"/>the queſtion, how it happend that Sibylls were not Ador'd as Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles? and ſhew that it is enough to confirm the former poſition, <hi>viz.</hi> That Devotion may be terminate in ſome finite Being, as ſupreme, though not in all appearances of extraordinary power. Theſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacles being remov'd, the next argument for the proof of the being of a Deity ſhall be examin'd, which is taken from that prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Topick of paternal love and care which is preſum'd to be ſuch as would not deceive his Son, by a ſucceſſive Tradition of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God (which is ſo univerſal, that Barbarians are not without it) which if falſe, would be ſuch an unnatural deceit, that Stage nor
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:98034:55"/>Hiſtory can parallel. This argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath more ſtrength from this conſideration, that as the Fathers would not be ſo unnatural to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their Sons, ſo would they not ſuffer themſelves to be deceived in matters of great moment. This is ſo probable, that it ſcarce admits of any ſuſpicion of its poſſibility of being otherwiſe; yet when it is examined by a Rigid and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til inquiry, it will be doubted whether the Forefathers might not commit that out of weakneſs, which they would not have done out of choice, could their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding have been better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd.</p>
            <p>How much reaſon fails in its general queſt, appears from the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:98034:56"/>conſideration of theſe arguments. I paſs now to a more particular Diſquiſition, <hi>how the unity of the Godhead is or can</hi> be known by principles of pure or <hi>uninlightned</hi> Reaſon.</p>
            <p>Although the ſuppoſal of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytheiſm, according to the manner how man frames a notion of God (which is by ſumming up all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and then concentring them in one Being after an infinite manner) implyes a contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the plurality of God ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes the poſſibility of more <hi>than all,</hi> which is ſo palpable a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, that the very naming of it is a ſufficient confutation; yet in ſtrictneſs of ſpeech, ſeeing the Reaſoner cannot attain to a clear
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:98034:56"/>and diſtinct knowledg of an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Being, how can he be ſaid to know God as one God, and it may take place amongſt the Theiſts, he muſt be ſeated in the Claſſis of the Athenian Votaries, and be eſteemed no wiſer than the inſcription which St. <hi>Paul</hi> cites, makes them who worſhip an unknown God; in which the Epithet ſuppoſes they were ignorant of what they ſaid, for if they had known him they could have diſtinguiſhed him from other Beings in the univerſe, for it is ſo eſſential to Unity to be diſtinguiſhed from other Beings, that if it be apprehended as it lies confuſed, it cannot properly be ſaid to be known, no more than the nature of Gold can be ſaid to be
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:98034:57"/>known when it meets with ſuch an Idiots Judgment, which is ſo far from being a Touchſtone, that it can only diſtinguiſh the Ore from common Sand. Beſides it is more than probable, that the Heathen had (neither can the Reaſoner have more on ſuch principles) only a confuſed notion of power and wiſdom in the World, not able to comprehend one being diſtinct from the reſt, ſo as to be pointed out by any certain and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Character, and an aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of all power and wiſdom ſummed up in <hi>one being.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might conclude this Diſquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on without any further ſurvey of Heathens opinions, did I not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that authority, though in this
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:98034:57"/>caſe may appear inſignificant to my purpoſe; yet may be urged againſt my poſition, if it be ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted, that the Heathens, <hi>Plato,</hi> with many others acknowledged but one God, and therefore by Chriſtian writers both antient and modern cited to confute Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm, which citations, I preſume, were rather made uſe of, to diſpoſe the minds of men for a belief of one God, than as convincing De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration, for it is plain that the Heathens in their moſt refined notions of a Deity have not fram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſuch an exact Idea of one God, as to quit the thoughts of Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm; for when they ſpake moſt Divinely, they oftentimes, as if they had forgot what they were
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:98034:58"/>ſpeaking of, or at leaſt ſenſible, that they could not comprehend it, inſtead <hi>of God,</hi> ſay <hi>Gods.</hi> I cannot but take notice of <hi>Socrates,</hi> ſo famous for natural Divinity, for oppoſing Heatheniſh Deities, when he ſpeaks of the excellent goodneſs of the Deity, and how that men were ſo much the more good as their actions had Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to the Divine; which ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſayes deſerved to be called Goſpel, had there not been a miſtake in the number, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Gods</hi> for <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might here detain the Reader by citation of opinions of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens (which is not pleaſant to me but when neceſſary) who may as well ſpend time in conſidering
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:98034:58"/>ſuch extravagant <hi>brain Idols,</hi> as viewing thoſe in Pagans Temples, but I ſhall only refer him to <hi>Tully, Seneca,</hi> or other famous Heathen Sophiſts, and he will find, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they ſpeak of the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, juſtice, and goodneſs of the Divine Being, as if they were Secretaries of Heaven; yet theſe by them are not attributed only to one God but Gods, and <hi>Dij</hi> in theſe high accounts of Divinity is as often uſed as <hi>Deus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To inſtance but in one cited by <hi>Tully, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de legib. Thales,</hi> who ſpeaks ſo Divinely, that he owns Providence, ubiquity and eminent power, with Wiſdom, which knows our thoughts, to be in ſome Divine Being; yet at laſt faſtens all theſe
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:98034:59"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:98034:59"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:98034:60"/>perfections in <hi>Dij,</hi> how much this favours of Polytheiſm or confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoughts, the Reader will confeſs when he traces <hi>Tully</hi> himſelf (who cites others). All that can be ſaid to exempt them from Polytheiſm is, that when they ſaid <hi>Dij,</hi> they intended inferiour Deities; This cannot reſcue them from the former imputation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a contradiction to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine Providence, Omniſcience, and other Attributes can be communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to any Being which is not infinite. To conclude this part of the Paragraph, all the ſeeming Divine ſentences of Heathens ſpeak promiſcuouſly of <hi>God</hi> or <hi>Gods,</hi> and make the Court of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſpeak in the Language of a
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:98034:60"/>mortal Monarch (Wee) which though a plural expreſſion without the help of a figure is known to repreſent a <hi>King;</hi> they were ſo unluckily ignorant, that although they had ſome notion of the Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, they could not expreſs what they had in confuſion conceived, as it too plainly appears from their wild diſcourſes of God, which if they had been on any other Subject, they would have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver intitled the Authors to the names of wiſe men.</p>
            <p>Let it not be objected, that the ſame may be argued againſt the Scripturiſt, which is againſt the <hi>Reaſoner;</hi> becauſe in holy Writings God is as well repreſented by an <hi>Elohim</hi> a plural number, as <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah</hi>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:98034:61"/>which is ſingular. To this objection it is enough to ſuggeſt, that there is not the ſame reaſon in Pagan writings to juſtifie ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, which ſeem to favour Polytheiſm, as in Holy Scripture. <hi>Moſes</hi> (when he expreſſes one God by a plural number) his language is ſuitable to the Hebrew Idiom or way of expreſſion, without the nice and myſterious Criticiſm to prove a Trinity; as it appears from Heathen Interpreters, as well as thoſe of the Jews, it hath been tranſlated as ſingular. So <hi>Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Page</hi> 35. <hi>Sect.</hi> 7. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, citing <hi>Moſes</hi>'s words. Add to this ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſideration, that he who wrote the Hiſtory of Creation,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:98034:61"/>wrote alſo the Law, in which man is confined to the worſhip of one God in the plaineſt terms, from which command there may be a reaſonable conjecture, that man in his corrupt ſtate is more prone to own plurality of Gods than pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs <hi>one,</hi> elſe why was this command in the front and ſo early given? I know it is, and may be ſaid, that the Preface as well as the Command was as an Antidote againſt the poyſon of the Egyptians Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous cuſtoms; yet Idolatry be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then ſo young (only a few <hi>Garden Deities, Leeks</hi> and <hi>Onions</hi> ador'd) it may be imagin'd that this Law was promulged to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move mens ignorance, which without Divine aſſiſtance is invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:98034:62"/>for the eye of the Soul in its decai'd ſtate is like one intoxicated, whoſe we kneſs multiplies a ſingle object, wherefore it was neceſſary that <hi>Iſrael,</hi> even to improvement of Knowledg as well as Religion, ſhould know there was but one God. Let this alſo be conſider'd, that in Pagan Divinity we find no ſuch diſtinguiſhing worſhip or character given to <hi>Jupiter,</hi> to ſhew that he was God. Are the other Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties but Deputies? (as ſome learned men ſay) or ſo reputed, for they were all ador'd: now in Scripture, there is not the leaſt favour or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſation granted to adore any Being but God, no not ſo much as his Repreſentators, Prophets and Apoſtles working wonders; This
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:98034:62"/>is enough to juſtifie the expreſſion of God by a plural number in Scripture, though not in Pagan writings; (beſides the Grammati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal help of a ſingular number with a plural without falſe Syntax or falſe ſenſe) The Heathens did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend God in ſuch a manner, as a plural number beſt ſuited with their thoughts, ſeeing the Univerſe was their God as appeared by their Deifi'd <hi>Pan,</hi> of whom there is this account</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> —</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Orpheus in Hymn.</hi> This may be further proved by a Teſtimony of <hi>lactantius. lib.</hi> 9. <hi>De falſe Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one</hi> who when he brings in <hi>Triſme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſt</hi> ſpeaking moſt Divinely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:98034:63"/>the Unity of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, ſaying <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which he tranſlates or pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphraſes on it, <hi>Ignitur Deo nomen non eſt, nec opus eſt proprio vocabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo niſi cum diſcrimen exigit multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whence it is plain, that the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude ſometimes apprehended God as the general power reigning in the World, though at other times they were more accurate in asking his name.</p>
            <p>But not to check inventions or methods, by which men frame the notion of one God, let the Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſician think of infinite power, wiſdom, juſtice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to art or rule, put them together, he will make ſuch an Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregate
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:98034:63"/>or Sum of perfections which man cannot naturally know, or by what one name to call it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide that of infinite, now how pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly Infinity in the natural mans ſenſe can be ſaid to be <hi>one,</hi> hath been ſaid before, it being like Eternity, of which we can ſpeak ſo little properly, that we can rather ſay what it is not, than what it is. Add to this, that the Reaſoner who frames a notion of a God by ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming up perfections, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not how one Attribute poiſes another, how power, wiſdom, ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and mercy bound one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he ſeems as much a Polytheiſt as he who own'd power in <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and wiſdom in <hi>Apollo,</hi> &amp;c. And can no more be ſaid to be a Theiſt,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:98034:64"/>than one whoſe education hath ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced him no further than the Alphabet, can be ſaid to be a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lologer, or he who only knows Letters, an Interpreter of words, before they have taken their places to form them. This inſtance, if it ſeem not ſo appoſite, yet I hope pardonable, ſeeing Chriſt himſelf diſdains not to be called the Word, which without his own expoſition would but imperfectly expreſs his nature, and <hi>Amelius</hi> a Platoniſt admir'd by <hi>Euſebius. lib.</hi> 11. <hi>de prepar. Evang. cap.</hi> 19.</p>
            <p>And call'd <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Becauſe he ſo much approved the compellation. Suppoſe a Novice who hath been only in the Porch of a Geometrical School, and learnt
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:98034:64"/>all kind of Lines in their ſeveral varieties, of which the moſt accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat draught muſt conſiſt, ſhall he be thought worthy of the name of a Painter who knows no proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the ſingle lines? this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance I preſume is ſo appoſite, that it will need no comment on it, and it giving me occaſion of a digreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from the Metaphyſical method of framing a notion of one God to one more ſuited to all appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion by ſimilitude, as <hi>Vives, Grotius, Morney,</hi> and others, who have illuſtrated the Unity of the Godhead by Analogy, <hi>viz.</hi> The Heavens, one Sun, one <hi>Primum mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile,</hi> and other inſtances of Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, as it appears in the World. How little impreſſion ſuch inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:98034:65"/>are like to make on ſome, who in their Philoſophical certainty conclude that there is no ſuch <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum mobile</hi> in the ſame Authors ſenſe, neither dare affirm there are no more lights of like nature, and influences, may be gueſt at by the reception and entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which later Hypotheſes have found.</p>
            <p>So he who endeavours to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate the Unity and Trinity in the Godhead by the three powers which are in one Soul, may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect his argument ſhould be as little prevalent; for that me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod which obligeth a Peripate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick to the belief of a Trinity, may perſwade the Platonick to believe a Quaternion; for he as zealouſly contends for that, as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:98034:65"/>to its ſeveral degrees of knowledg, as the other was for his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or three powers in the rational Soul: and ſurely the <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonicks</hi> did admire the number 4. elſe it had not been ſo ſolemnly uſed in their Oaths. Let it be urged that God may be known by ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, &amp; although there be but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect and ſmall footſteps of his <hi>Being</hi> to be traced by the <hi>Reaſoner;</hi> yet according to proportion, by one Attribute there may be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of all, as the proverbiall ſpeech of an <hi>Herculean</hi> draught from a foot (and if I may ſtretch the letter of the Proverb) a little finger. If ſuch objections ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to the Readers thoughts, I only deſire him to re-collect, or
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:98034:66"/>look back to the former part of the Diſquiſitions, in which it was never granted, that man by reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing can have any ſuch knowledg of any Attribute, ſo as it ſhall be a Rule to him infallibly to judg of the nature of God without Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and the laſt appeals made to it. I am not ignorant that the primitive Fathers, (to inſtance in one, <hi>Minutius Foelix</hi>) made uſe of ſimilitude to convince the World of the Unity of the Godhead, <hi>Dux unus Apibus, Dux unus in Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus;</hi> yet this was intended ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for illuſtration than ſtrict proof; neither is there violence done to the Divine example, whilſt the Reaſoner diſowns ſimilitudes in caſe that demonſtration is juſtly
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:98034:66"/>expected, for although God is pleaſed to diſcover himſelf by ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudes, he expects not that his Being ſhould be proved by that method.</p>
            <p>The Reconciler who ſuppoſes the Being of God and Providence. <hi>Page</hi> 4. of his Preface, cautions us to beware of ſimilitudes whilſt we would have a true conception of him. <hi>page</hi> 12. <hi>Attributes which we cannot poſſibly know, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he tell us, and then ſays, we ſhould not conclude or gueſs about them by Analogies, to things of a nature infinitely diſtant from his, or by maxims fram'd according to the nature of inferiour being.</hi> Let not this argument which ſeem; to have its foundation in practice
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:98034:67"/>prejudice the Reaſoner, for I ſhall no further make uſe of it than rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon muſt allow, and the authority cited ſhall have another ratificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of its ſtrength, by an appeal to the Reaſoner who helps his thoughts by art, and impartial and unbyaſs'd induſtry; who by the conduct of his own reaſon will ſcarce find out that narrow path which will lead him to the infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble knowledg of one God, for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the utmoſt peruſal of his own arguments concerning him, he will be oblig'd to deſcribe himſelf by a name ſuitable to his thoughts, which if he do, he will be in ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence whether he ought to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Theiſt or Polytheiſt, this bold preſumption is founded on the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:98034:67"/>former poſition. <hi>Viz.</hi> That the Reaſoner hath only a general knowledg of power undiſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed in the World. That a groſs and imperfect knowledg in a looſe and common way of ſpeech is enough to juſtifie the Language which calls a Being, one which in ſtrictneſs is not ſo. As a late Author inſtances in <hi>Rome,</hi> which retains its name; although the City is not the ſame, which firſt took that name, and there are <hi>Protean</hi> bodies which each mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment change; yet retain the ſame name. Such compariſons, or ſuch expreſſions may ſerve to expreſs things finite, words being as Coin, or rather the Stamp upon it (which oftentimes is ſo far from repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:98034:68"/>the perſon of a King, that there is much neceſſity of a Motto, to tell whoſe Image it is; as Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the infancy of their Art were forced to ſupply the defect of their Pencil by their Pens, and make men Readers, not Spectators of Pictures.) But the ſtrict Reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as he is careful in frameing notions of things, ſo he will be careful in giving names, or ſaying any thing concerning number or nature of that Being which he cannot comprehend; <hi>Infinite,</hi> as <hi>infinite</hi> is beyond the reach of our underſtanding, whence it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, that when any thing is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd of an object as infinite, ſo far the affirmation will be doubted of as uncertain, that aſſent which
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:98034:68"/>paſſes apprehenſion, muſt paſs for ignorance, and can only be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſted by an implicit faith. Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite would not be infinite, could it be apprehended as an adaequate object of humane knowledg; though it were as nigh as poſſible. The French Philoſopher modeſtly took the liberty to make a term of Art, a gives the old World a name more ſuitable to mans ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, than that which it had been known by in ſeveral ages; for finite, calling it <hi>indefinite,</hi> which is ſomething in its own nature which hath bounds, therefore its dimenſions poſſible to be known; but no man can determine any thing concerning infinity either as to number or quality, ſeeing the
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:98034:69"/>object he judges of is beyond his reach. He who attributes any <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty</hi> to a <hi>Subject,</hi> is ſuppoſed to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the nature or <hi>form</hi> of it: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, he like the man in the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, who having not fully his ſight recovered, may call men <hi>Trees,</hi> or faſten impoſſibilities on the <hi>Subject,</hi> leaſt qualifie it by the notion he frames of it, with a power to make impoſſibilities not to be ſo; as the Reconciler <hi>of Reaſon and Religion</hi> inſtances in the <hi>French Virtuoſo,</hi> who concludes the poſſibility of a <hi>Hill</hi> without a <hi>Valley,</hi> not conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Alex. Aphrodiſ. de fato,</hi> p. 135. To make ſuch aſſertions ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:98034:69"/>plauſible, all that can be ſaid, is, that <hi>impoſſibilities</hi> ceaſe to be ſuch, when they have relation to God, as the <hi>vaſt bulk</hi> of the Earth appears as a <hi>point</hi> or as nothing, when conſidered in reſpect to the motion of ſome Stars. This aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion ſhews the Authors ingenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and modeſty, but gives little ſatisfaction to the Reaſoner: for to conclude God can do impoſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, becauſe he is infinite, is to prove a propoſition by a <hi>medium</hi> equally obſcure. It is a difficult task to find truth in general, and he who is nice, will be cautious how he attributes any <hi>propertie</hi> to a <hi>Being,</hi> which he doth not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, but more eſpecially when he is to ſpeak of <hi>one,</hi> whoſe <hi>attributes</hi>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:98034:70"/>are ſo nearly united to his being, that they cannot be diſtinguiſhed from it. This difficulty of frame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the notion of God, made ſome Heathens look on the Deity as an <hi>univerſal power,</hi> or an <hi>aggregat of all perfections</hi> in the World: for though they ſeem to ſpeak Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinely of <hi>God</hi> as <hi>one,</hi> I am apt to think they ſpeak in the Language of Jewellers who call one kind of Margarites <hi>unions</hi> (becauſe firſt they were found <hi>ſingle</hi>) when dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly experience ſhews <hi>many</hi> are hatcht in the ſame <hi>ſhell.</hi> Here I might make a ſtop and pity the <hi>Ethnic</hi> and the <hi>ſecular Reaſoner,</hi> who like <hi>Apodes</hi> (Birds on the wing) hover in contemplation without feet to reſt on (for whoſe
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:98034:70"/>ſupport, though nature hath made proviſion; yet with greater diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty and danger than for other familiar works of nature) for though it muſt be confeſt as a <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> eminent both for Chriſtian and <hi>Pagan Oratory,</hi> ſays in his <hi>Octavia</hi> that the Heathens did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways own one God and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence but knew not how to point it out. This confeſt, helps the Heathen or Reaſoner very little; for as it was ſaid in the beginning of this Diſquiſition, that he who hath ſuch a Roving phancy as not to diſtinguiſh <hi>God</hi> from other <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> deſerv'd not the name of a <hi>Theiſt.</hi> If it be again objected that the <hi>unity</hi> of the <hi>God-head</hi> hath been known to thoſe who had no
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:98034:71"/>opportunity or abilities to read holy Scripture, yet ſpake ſentences which are matter of Chriſtian faith To inſtance in one famous verſe.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>This cannot help the Reaſoner in this <hi>Article of belief,</hi> for it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſaying of a <hi>Sibyl</hi> it cannot be called the <hi>dictate</hi> of pure reaſon, for though we know not how, yet it muſt be acknowledged, that ſo much as they ſpake truly of God and Chriſt came from Revelation in ſuch a Way as none can deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. Thus far I have endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſhew Reaſons defect in its firſt and chiefeſt diſcoveries, when it puts it ſelf on the <hi>rack,</hi> ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:98034:71"/>only to a Sceptical uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. It now remains, that I meet with another objection, which may ſeem ſo conſiderable, that I may not paſs it by without taking notice, that it may be retorted from the former part of the Diſquiſition, that I conclude the Gentiles or Ethnicks had not the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of a Deity (neither could properly be called Theiſts), which aſſertion ſeems too cruel and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable: for ſome eminent in learning allow, that the Heathens in their Theory and practice, (if not ſav'd in ſome ſenſe, may be exempt from Damnation, becauſe they had a <hi>Law</hi> from God, and by that Law were to be judged. Add to this, that the Heathens are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:98034:72"/>to be Judges of actions mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally <hi>good</hi> and <hi>evil, juſt</hi> and <hi>unjuſt,</hi> and juſtice in man is the ſame with that which is in God, though in an inferiour degree. Let this be granted; It will not help the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner in ſetting out his guide, for although the rules of Juſtice are the ſame in the <hi>Ethnick</hi> and the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> (and ſome of the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments</hi> being <hi>Reaſons dictates,</hi> promulg'd and made Law by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Legiſlation) yet they ſhall not be judged in the <hi>ſame way and manner,</hi> ſuppoſe the Heathen ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly obſerve his <hi>Legem Talionis,</hi> and demands an <hi>Eye</hi> for an <hi>Eye,</hi> or a <hi>Tooth</hi> for a <hi>Tooth,</hi> as the holy Scripture expreſſes it, or to ſpeak in the poetical ſaying which <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stotle</hi>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:98034:72"/>lays down as a rule approv'd by Rhadamanthus <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Ariſt. lib.</hi> 5. Such obſervation of natures Law will juſtifie the Heathen, not the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. The Reaſoner may alſo urge that <hi>Tully, Plato, Seneca,</hi> and other Sophies have been Authors of ſuch ſentences which have ſuch a near alliance to Scripture, that only the Authors names can diſtinguiſh them from it. This granted, will not help the Reaſoner, for he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not prove them <hi>emanations</hi> of a Heathens mind, or convince the World of the certainty of their not being borrowed from Divine Revelation, mixing their own thoughts with ſome notions taken from Scripture, as ſome have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:98034:73"/>to prove, which will appear more probable, if the Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick be conſidered in his confuſed way of ſpeaking of God, and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent expreſſions of him, which will give way for a concluſion, That they certainly knew a <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> above themſelves, but what it was were uncertain, for had they as certainly known his nature as they ſeemed aſſured of his <hi>Being,</hi> there had not been ſuch variety of opinions concerning him, for theſe <hi>notions</hi> in mans mind are <hi>unalterable,</hi> and although diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe or <hi>artificial</hi> ways may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found them, when concluſions are to be drawn, and ſo ſeem variable; yet in themſelves conſidered can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be changed. Wherefore it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:98034:73"/>granted, that God is known by pure Reaſon as to his Being, and ſome of his attributes; yet by this imperfect notion the Reaſoner can be no more called a Theiſt, and ſaid to know God, than he who ſeeing ſome few, or all the propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of a man drawn or painted, can be ſaid to know his <hi>Craſis</hi> or Conſtitution, or what humour is predominant. If a ſimilitude may be admitted in this caſe, it may be ſaid that he who paſſes judgment of the nature of the Deity by thoſe lineaments of <hi>juſtice</hi> and <hi>mercy, power</hi> and <hi>knowledg,</hi> which are in man, he will be as ignorant of the nature of God as the other of the <hi>Craſis</hi> or Conſtitution of a man, for as the one cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:98034:74"/>by the draught what humour is predominant; neither can the other know in which attribute God takes moſt delight. Beſides, if mere natural evidence is to be ſet up judg of <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>unjuſt,</hi> without reſpect to the <hi>Divine will,</hi> a great part of Religion will be diſputed, and the <hi>Chriſtian Creed</hi> contracted into too narrow a compaſs, ſome of its <hi>Articles</hi> (according to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of paſſing judgment) being in danger not to be believ'd; and Chriſtianity would not be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd much above that height which King <hi>Agrippa</hi> arriv'd at, men being but <hi>almoſt perſwaded to be Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hitherto Reaſon hath been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd in its queſt, concerning the
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:98034:74"/>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of the <hi>God-head,</hi> but before this diſquiſition is concluded, I cannot but take notice of that fam'd inſtance in <hi>Plato</hi> (cited by <hi>Euſebius, de praeparat. Evang. lib. undec. c. Dec. tert.</hi> who made the unity of the Godhead as a <hi>Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteriſtick</hi> or <hi>token,</hi> by which <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onyſius</hi> ſhould diſcern, whether his Letters or Epiſtles were <hi>jocular</hi> or <hi>ſerious.</hi> This ſeems to ſpeak the Author naturally Orthodox, but doth not ſufficiently juſtifie him, and undoubtedly free him from the imputation of Polytheiſm, or a confus'd notion of the Deity, for it may be doubted whether he us'd that <hi>Beginning with one God</hi> as a <hi>mark</hi> of his more <hi>ſerious buſineſs,</hi> rather than to ſignifie his <hi>ſetled opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion;</hi>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:98034:75"/>becauſe it would ſavour too much of a narrow and envious Spirit, not becoming a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, to have communicated that as a ſecret to <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> and not ſo clearly and ingenuouſly declared it to the reſt of the World in the whole <hi>ſeries</hi> of his Diſcourſes. It may be alſo a wonder that he could at any time write <hi>Jocularly,</hi> and playing with the Deities, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the term <hi>Gods</hi> to be as a Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net to ſeal his more trivial ſecrecy, or leſs accurate writings, except it can be thought, that he, as a <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> derided and laught at the Heathens Idolatry, being ſerious when <hi>Deus</hi> came into his mind, but laughing when he thought of <hi>Dij.</hi> This may be one plauſible
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:98034:75"/>way to confirm the uſual applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Plato</hi>'s Epiſtolar <hi>Mark</hi> or <hi>Sign,</hi> but it is hard to be imagin'd, if his ſtile and manner of writing is conſiderd.</p>
            <p>That which is ſaid of Heathens ignorance, will not be eaſily refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by citations taken from <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyrius, Proclus</hi> or <hi>Plotinus,</hi> or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Platoniſts, ſeeing it may be preſum'd, that they entertain'd the ſame opinion of the Deity which their Maſter had. Now how far the <hi>Platonick</hi> Doctrine is to be embraced, may appear from the conſideration of the Diſcourſes <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſome have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to accommodate to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>ſecond Perſon</hi> in the <hi>Holy Trinity;</hi> For the <hi>ſecond Principle</hi>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:98034:76"/>in <hi>Plato</hi>'s ſenſe implies more, or rather is different from the <hi>perſonal diſtinction</hi> in the Trinity, as it is matter of Chriſtian Belief. If it might be thought proper to vye Authority with Authority, I could inſtance in Heathens Eminent in Dignity, Morality and Learning, <hi>Antoninus</hi> and <hi>Severus</hi> who were not free from the thoughts of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytheiſm, as may be conjectur'd from the Language of their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <hi>Profeſſor</hi> of Philoſophy, <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and. Aphrod.</hi> in his book <hi>De fato, p.</hi> 135. which ſpeaks of the Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in a plural number, and attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes Omniſcience and Preſcience (which is the attribute of <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>only true God</hi>) to <hi>Dij,</hi> or <hi>Gods</hi>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:98034:76"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. This Language may be preſum'd to be ſuited to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours apprehenſion of the Deity. This alſo may be conſidered, <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nophon,</hi> who in a pleaſant Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe ſeems not altogether to ſpeak his own ſenſe or Language, but that which generally was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, ſays <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. which ſhews that the Unity of this <hi>ſupreme power,</hi> was not ſo apprehended to be infallib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly denominated <hi>one</hi> as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> implies, which may not be tranſlated <hi>is,</hi> but <hi>ſeems, Zenoph. in convivio.</hi> If this citation (as <hi>Table Diſcourſe</hi>) may ſeem too familiar to bear the weight of Authority in ſtrict ways of arguing, let the <hi>Authour</hi> be
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:98034:77"/>conſidered, when he ſpeaks moſt ſeriouſly, and when an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary appearance of an Enemy ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd his thoughts to retirement, and engaged him to Devotion, it will appear doubtful, whether he was <hi>Theiſt</hi> or <hi>Polytheiſt,</hi> at the ſame breath confounding <hi>Deus</hi> and <hi>Dij,</hi> beginning with the one, and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the other, ſaying theſe words, concluding his Oration to the Souldiers. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Zen. de exped Cyri-pag.</hi> 296.</p>
            <p>Hitherto the Deity hath been conſidered, as it may be ſaid to be known to the Reaſoner, and the next diſquiſition is. <hi>What certain
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:98034:77"/>knowledg of the nature of the Soul and its immortality can be attain'd by mere Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the Eye cannot ſee it ſelf without a Mirror or Glaſs, ſo the Soul cannot know it ſelf, at leaſt as to its duration or immortality without Revelation. It is a diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult task to prove its exiſtence, much more the eternal continuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it, as appears by the <hi>French</hi> Philoſopher, who ſeems to glory of his Invention, when he had (as he thought) found a way to convince the Sceptick of its diſtinct exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence from the body. Wherefore (according to the former method) let his argument be examin'd, which concludes the exiſtence of the Soul to be more demonſtrable
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:98034:78"/>than that of the Body, becauſe that which paſſes judgment on all other Beings, it ſelf muſt exiſt. This conſequence may not be deny'd, and it muſt be alſo concluded, that the Soul only paſſes judgment on objects, for the <hi>corporeal Organs</hi> are ſo far from diſcerning other ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, that without the Soul they cannot ſee themſelves, the eyes can ſee no more than a pair of <hi>Spectacles,</hi> (if the Soul is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident in them to judg of objects) or the Ear hear any more than an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or the Noſe ſmell any more than a <hi>Cenſer</hi> can the Incenſe which is burnt in it. This is enough to convince the Reaſoner of the exiſtence of a Spirit or <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> in a human body which is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:98034:78"/>from it, did not the definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which ſays the Soul is <hi>res cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans,</hi> confound Reaſon it ſelf whilſt it conſiders it. For he who diſputes nicely or ſceptically, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this definition may doubt whether <hi>Brutes</hi> may not be <hi>res cogitantes,</hi> and conſequently have Souls of the <hi>ſame kind</hi> with the <hi>humane</hi> only differenc'd by <hi>gradual</hi> perfection; ſeeing ſome in former ages have not been ſo Dogmatical as to conclude poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively that Brutes have no kind of cogitation or <hi>petty Reaſonings,</hi> as appears from <hi>Platarch</hi>'s <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> with this Title, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; and perhaps ſome in this age would not deny them to be <hi>res cogitantes,</hi> did not
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:98034:79"/>this conſequence attend the aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>immortality</hi> of <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Souls</hi> which the Religious man cannot or may not imagine. Let this alſo be conſidered, that this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument for the proof of the Souls exiſtence, as much as that above cited to prove the <hi>Being</hi> of God, will be thought defective, for this, as others, borrows its force from a ſuppoſition, which the Sceptic will not allow, neither will the more ſober man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ook upon that definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Soul as perfect, which may be accommodated to other Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as it is above ſuggeſted. In the next place let an argument of a later Author, one eminent for Learning and Invention be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd, who ſays the <hi>nature of God
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:98034:79"/>is as intelligible as the nature of other Beings</hi> (which aſſertion in ſome ages of the Church would have been thought a juſt cauſe of putting the Author in the Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of the <hi>Anomi</hi> or <hi>Anomaei,</hi> who by ſome of the Fathers were eſteem'd Erronious in a high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, if not Haeretical) and alſo attempts to make the nature of the Soul as intelligible and as eaſie to be diſcern'd as the Sun (from which he borrows inſtances to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs his more refin'd thoughts) whilſt he defines a Spirit, a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance which hath <hi>ſelf penetration,</hi> ſelf contraction, and ſelf dilatati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in his book of the immortality of the Soul. This ſeems to help Reaſon in the conceiving the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:98034:80"/>of a Spirit, but really the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors notion of extenſion is not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible, for it ſuppoſes the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of many Spirits being ſo contracted, that they muſt appear to the apprehenſion as one, ſo that the mind cannot diſtinguiſh them, and it is impoſſible it can, whilſt they are couch't in a ſingle ſuperficies not diviſible into another, not ſo much as in thought, therefore ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this method the mind muſt have <hi>falſe apprehenſions</hi> whilſt many Spirits are ſo contracted, that it muſt apprehend many <hi>Individu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als</hi> as one <hi>Individual</hi> in a more confus'd conception than <hi>Genus</hi> and <hi>Species</hi> are conceiv'd, with the numerous <hi>Beings</hi> which are comprehended in thoſe <hi>terms</hi> of
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:98034:80"/>
               <hi>Art.</hi> Let this alſo be conſider'd, that when <hi>Myriads</hi> of Spirits are confin'd to one <hi>extenſion,</hi> that being but <hi>one</hi> muſt be a ſubſtance com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to <hi>all,</hi> ſo that the Spirits can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not decide <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum,</hi> ſeeing by a kind of <hi>coalition</hi> they are uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in ſubſtance. And it muſt be alſo imagin'd that the <hi>forms</hi> and <hi>faculties</hi> of thoſe Spirits muſt be confus'd in one <hi>ſubſtance</hi> or <hi>exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> or at leaſt for a time be ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from their <hi>proper ſubſtance,</hi> which is more difficult to be imagin'd, than the Souls taking a farwell from the Body for ſome ſhort time, (which is very impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable) and then return again. It is confeſt, the Author defends his definition of a Spirit in a plauſible
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:98034:81"/>way, and perhaps will think theſe objections inconſiderable, however my deſign is anſwered, if it ſhews how Reaſon is confounded in framing a notion of a Spirit, which was declar'd ſo eaſie to be appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended. If it is alſo ſaid, that this is no new or monſtrous aſſertion; for the Schools and antient Fathers have determined that Thouſands of Angels may be preſent in the leaſt quantity, a <hi>point,</hi> or if there could be any leſs extenſion: let it be conſider'd, that theſe poſitions were laid down to take off the groſs ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of the vulgar, who could ſcarce ſtretch their imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion beyond material Beings, and frame notions of Spirits ſuitable to them, but did never undertake to
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:98034:81"/>explain the manner, or to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine whether Spirits were <hi>extended</hi> or not. Hitherto the two <hi>rational Aſsertors</hi> of the Souls immortality being conſidered, this Diſquiſition ſhall be concluded with this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, <hi>viz.</hi> The Souls eternal duration depends on the concourſe of Divine Providence, which can conſerve it or annihilate it, and this depends on God's pleaſure or Will, of which the mere Reaſoner muſt be ignorant; wherefore it is no great wonder, if ſome antient Sophies ſpake doubtfully of the Souls immortality. That which is ſaid is enough to ſhew the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty of the Reaſoners know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg in this queſt concerning the Soul; but perhaps it may be urg'd,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:98034:82"/>that mere Reaſoners, <hi>Plato</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have concluded its <hi>exiſtence</hi> and <hi>immortality.</hi> This may be confeſt, yet the Divine ſentences in their writings, which ſpeak this, ſeem rather <hi>Enthuſiaſtick</hi> (or at leaſt an <hi>innate</hi> or <hi>common notion</hi>) than the deduction of the diſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive faculties. For if the Divine ſentences which lye ſcattered in <hi>Plato</hi>'s Books, and the <hi>media</hi> be weigh'd by which he made thoſe concluſions, they will ſeem to be a building with a glorious ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructure without a foundation proportion'd to its weight, or like an <hi>Arch</hi> which Mathematicians ſpeak of, hanging in the Air, poiz'd by its own proportions, without a Buttreſs or foundation. <hi>Plato</hi>'s
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:98034:82"/>ſentences may give him the title <hi>Divine,</hi> but his reaſons, by which he proves them, ſpeak him but a <hi>man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hitherto I have diſcover'd Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons defect, or dim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight in diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the nature of God and the Soul, it will now be proper to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter on another diſquiſition, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whether Grace in the Act of Faith alters the eye-ſight, and in what ſenſe Reaſon is laid aſide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The negative part of the firſt Clauſe of this diſquiſition is the Reaſoners poſition, who concludes that Grace doth not <hi>alter the eye-ſight, but only brings the Object nigher,</hi> allowing the Believer no alteration, or better diſpoſition of the eye of his Soul, by which he
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:98034:83"/>thinks he can the better effect what he deſigns, <hi>viz.</hi> To ſet up every private perſon as an Umpire, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible in defining matters of faith as a Council. For by the ſame Reaſon he will not allow the eye-ſight alter'd in a private perſon, he will deny any alteration of it (which is that which makes it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible) in a Council. Thus ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the private Reaſoner, and rational members of a <hi>Council</hi> to diſcover truth no otherwiſe than by a mere <hi>natural ſight (the object being brought nigher)</hi> he concludes them equally infallible. This <hi>project</hi> is built on a weak foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which will appear to be ſo, by conſidering the unaptneſs or indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition in the Soul to diſcern truth
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:98034:83"/>from falſehood in Religious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, which is plain from the vain attempts of Reaſon in the diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of it. And the indiſpoſition of the mind, which is not ſuch as can be removed by frequent acts, which make a habit to facilitate know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg in Arts and Sciences; for the Soul in this caſe, after the utmoſt of its endeavours to improve its un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, muſt be beholding to, or dependent on ſome <hi>power</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides its own, which muſt help it as well as <hi>bring the object nigher.</hi> For if we do but conſider the ſeveral ways, by which the underſtanding is improv'd, we muſt conclude it is not by its own power. For the believers Soul muſt have Divine aid or aſſiſtance either <hi>mediate</hi> or
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:98034:84"/>
               <hi>immediate</hi> in the act of Faith which muſt be call'd <hi>Grace;</hi> which if it be only ſuppos'd to diſpoſe the <hi>Organs,</hi> as there is a neceſſity of it in <hi>mad men,</hi> and thoſe which are <hi>Fools</hi> only by a bodily defect, which renders thoſe parts uſeleſs which were deſigned for the ſervice of the Soul in the exerciſe of her Functions, it is more than <hi>bringing the object nigher.</hi> Logicians (which is only a hard name for ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional men) ſay there is <hi>potentia prima,</hi> which renders a blind man as capable of ſeeing, if the <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans</hi> were well diſpoſed, as he who hath a perfect ſight. And thoſe who ſay all Souls are equal, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the fault is in the <hi>Organs</hi> (if a man after the utmoſt of induſtry
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:98034:84"/>joyned with advantage) is a Fool for this Reaſon, becauſe his Soul is as capable of knowledg, as that of the greateſt Sophies. This in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance will agree with the Reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner's caſe, who will allow no man to be a Spiritual Fool but on his own default, wherefore he ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es the interpretation of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to ſignifie the <hi>ſenſual man,</hi> which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be allowed; for if he mean the <hi>debaucht Epicure,</hi> then it would follow that every <hi>ſober man</hi> would be aſſured of finding truth: for if there is not any fault in the eye of Reaſon (ſenſuality according to his aſſertion being removed) what can hinder? for if the eye is well diſpoſed, and the object high, the the eye cannot but ſee. This is
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:98034:85"/>ſo certain, that there is a natural ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of it, but the caſe is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in diſcerning ſpiritual truth. For the moſt ſober Heathens heave complained they were in darkneſs.</p>
            <q>Quancum mortalia caecae Pectora noctis habent?</q>
            <p>The natural frame and indiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the mind occaſioned this invincible ignorance, which may be ſo call'd, ſeeing it cannot be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved by humane Art or Induſtry, any more than a <hi>mad man</hi> can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore himſelf to a <hi>right mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That God can improve the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding is as evident as he can render it leſs perfect, which is plain from the puniſhment of our firſt
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:98034:85"/>forefather, who by his default for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited much of his Reaſoning fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty which was leſs perfect than in innocency; This cannot be deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, although the manner how the <hi>natural light</hi> was diminiſht, may puzle thoſe who will ſtrictly exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min it: For to diminiſh the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding according to thoſe who make <hi>cognitation</hi> the <hi>form of the Soul,</hi> is to make it to be <hi>leſs</hi> a <hi>Soul,</hi> which will not be allowed in Legick or Metaphyſicks, or according to that opinion which calls it a <hi>facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> or <hi>power</hi> of the mind to draw concluſions, it is hard to imagine how it ſhould be diſabled, except God uncreate or withdraw ſome perfection, or at leaſt his <hi>Grace</hi> or <hi>Divine aſſiſtance,</hi> which is as much
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:98034:86"/>if not more neceſſary for preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it in its due exerciſe of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in Religious debates, than the concourſe of providence which hinders the World from turning to its <hi>firſt nothing.</hi> The former opinion cannot be allowed, the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter if granted, will ſerve for the proof of the former aſſertion, for if it be (as it muſt be) allow'd that God hath and can make the Soul leſs perfect by withdrawing his Grace, he can, and doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it by ſupplies of the ſame; alſo The truth of this cannot be denyed, although it may ſeem obſcure, if it meet with the Reaſoner, who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps will be as much puzled with the word <hi>Grace,</hi> as he is with the word <hi>Schiſm.</hi> Which demur will
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:98034:86" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſoon be removed if Grace be taken for <hi>Divine aſſiſtance,</hi> which perfects the underſtanding, although the manner how it is done, cannot be otherwiſe than conjecturally ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed; For the ſtrict Reaſoner ſays, if the matter of Fact be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, <hi>whats</hi> and <hi>hows,</hi> not and not to hinder aſſent; wherefore it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing proved that there is a neceſſity of Divine aſſiſtance, 'tis not ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to examine ſtrictly the manner any more, than when we take it granted, that a <hi>Spirit</hi> can act on <hi>matter</hi> though the invention cannot imagine <hi>how,</hi> It is enough to conclude the truth of the former aſſertion, if God in the Act of faith do only excite notions in the mind, not only by propoſal of objects
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:98034:87"/>nigher, but by direction of the <hi>wil</hi> to give its <hi>aſſent,</hi> without which theſe notions or concluſions would have been dormant, or at leaſt doubtful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entertain'd by mere Reaſon fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing its own conduct. Before I diſpatch this part of the Diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, it is neceſſary to prevent what may be objected from the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer inſtance, <hi>viz.</hi> If <hi>Adam</hi> in his <hi>pure naturals</hi> had a diſtinct know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of God, and conſequently could have aſſented to all the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Religion without any other aſſiſtance than the bare pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal of them with appeals to his own Reaſon, laying aſide ſenſuali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (which muſt be allow'd to be the occaſion of his fall without ſtraining <hi>Cabaliſtical Divinity,</hi>
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:98034:87"/>which calls it <hi>forbidden fruit</hi>) ſo his poſterity may be abſtracting their thoughts from ſenſual objects arrive at the ſame degree of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection: This granted (which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be) will not qualifie the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner for Chriſtian belief; for could he ſuppoſe himſelf indow'd with the ſame faculties with which <hi>innocency</hi> was inveſted, he will be but a <hi>Viator</hi> (as the Schools ſay) more imperfect than the Chriſtian, not a <hi>Comprehenſor</hi> of matters of faith. Some <hi>Scholaſticks</hi> have been ſo far from concluding, that the knowledg which <hi>Adam</hi> had of God at leaſt as <hi>Triunus,</hi> was purely natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, that they doubted not to call it infus'd, for this reaſon (as well as the Authority of St. <hi>Auſtin. lib.
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:98034:88"/>undec. de Geneſi ad liter.</hi> becauſe it is not probable that God would ſuffer the <hi>Protoplaſt</hi> to be ignorant of that which was matter of faith to all his poſterity; And it may be ſafely concluded, that <hi>Adam</hi>'s Chriſtian poſterity give aſſent to the whole Sacred Volume of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by the ſame method and means by which <hi>Adam</hi> aſſented to, and believ'd that <hi>Synopſis</hi> of the whole Goſpel, <hi>The ſeed of the Woman ſhall bruiſe the Serpents head.</hi> If it is ſaid that <hi>Adam</hi>'s poſterity have a meaſure of knowledg, as much greater than that of their firſt fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, as the <hi>ſecond Adam</hi> is juſtly exalted above the firſt; yet this advance of knowledg owes not its Original to mere <hi>natural powers.</hi>
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:98034:88"/>For though the <hi>Chriſtian Believer</hi> (without breach of modeſty) may be ſaid to know more than his <hi>firſt Forefather;</hi> yet that higher degree of knowledg doth not only owe its improvement to a fuller declaration of <hi>God's Will</hi> in the <hi>latter,</hi> than in the <hi>firſt Goſpel</hi> preacht to <hi>Adam</hi> by God himſelf, but alſo to the <hi>Divine ſupplyes,</hi> which are proportion'd to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the Revelation; otherwiſe the Chriſtian could no more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve his large <hi>Creed,</hi> than it can be imagin'd, <hi>Adam</hi> could have comprehended the ſum of it, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd to him in few words without Divine interpretation or aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>If this inſtance ſeem not cloſe to the queſtion, let the <hi>will</hi> and the
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:98034:89"/>underſtanding be two eyes of faith, though by ſome one is called blind <hi>Caeca poteſtas,</hi> which error is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by later Philoſophy) be examin'd, and they will in their pure naturals be found defective. For as in naturals 'tis not enough that the eye is well diſpoſed, but a certain poſition of the object, and direction of the eye is neceſſary for ſome Diſcoveries, ſo although 'tis allow'd that Reaſon is no more <hi>new Reaſon</hi> by <hi>Grace,</hi> than an <hi>eye is a new eye,</hi> which by skilful directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons diſcerns that which it ſaw not before; yet this aſſiſtance though it do not frame ſight, but direct the eye, 'tis enough to deſtroy that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition which ſays in <hi>ſpiritual Viſion only the object is brought nigher.</hi>
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:98034:89"/>Add to this the mere diſpoſal of <hi>Media</hi> in order to perfect Viſion and it will give way for this aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that Divine aſſiſtance is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, for we muſt acknowledg, that ſeveral <hi>concluſions</hi> have been paſſed as true which before were doubted of, when a quick and happy inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath found a fit <hi>medium</hi> to prove them, or at leaſt render them more eaſie to be underſtood. To inſtance in that which is neareſt to man, his own Soul, its exiſtence is better apprehended by being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to ſome <hi>thin air,</hi> which hath power, though inviſible. Beſides it is beyond diſpute, that ſome ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural power infuſeth notions in dreams, which the Soul it ſelf could not excite. I diſpute not
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:98034:90"/>whether there are any ſuch in theſe days, 'tis enough to ſhew, that the Divine method without violence to Reaſon hath made ſuch diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in ſome ages of the Church, and may continue his aſſiſtance (though not in the ſame manner, for that would not appear conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with the ſetled and more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſtate of the Church) to help Reaſon in giving its aſſent to <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine truth.</hi> I need add no more for the confutation of the Reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners poſition than the propoſal of the Diſcourſe in the former diſqu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, which ſhews that there is a <hi>Beam</hi> in the eye of Reaſon, which if not removed, renders it ſo dim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſighted that it cannot diſcern the <hi>Elements</hi> and firſt <hi>principles</hi> of
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:98034:90"/>Religion, which are rudely in mans mind, and need ſome aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance for the due compoſure of the thoughts concerning God and his worſhip; wherefore let the Reaſoner conſider Grace but as a Chirurgians hand which couches a <hi>Pearl</hi> on the eye, or takes away the <hi>Gutta ſerena;</hi> Yet by this act the ſight is better, and this cannot be without alteration. Add to this the propoſal of objects and the diſpoſition of the eye and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia (which the eye it ſelf cannot diſpoſe) is enough to ſhew that Grace by ſuch acts may be ſaid to have <hi>alter'd</hi> the <hi>ſight,</hi> which might be rendred obſcure and confuſed by default of the <hi>medium</hi> or Organ; for as the Soul looks through the
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:98034:91"/>eye as a Glaſs, which if ſullied or diſcolour'd by any Diſeaſe, the judgment is paſs'd according to the tincture which is in the eye, not in the object, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently is as ill a Judg of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, as he who views objects with <hi>colour'd Proſpectives</hi> or any <hi>Catoptrical device</hi> to deceive the eye; ſo in ſpiritual Viſion the Soul looks with the eyes which have the diſeaſe, therefore 'tis not probable it ſhould diſcern its own malady, much leſs diſcover truth. To conclude this part of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition, it may be confidently affirmed that Grace <hi>alters</hi> the <hi>ſight,</hi> though it do but take off a <hi>film</hi> or <hi>ſcale,</hi> as from St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s eyes,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:98034:91"/>which the natural man by his own power is no more able to remove than the eye by dropping tears (a way to put out eyes rather than reſtore them) can do as much as any <hi>eye-water</hi> which the <hi>Oculiſt</hi> can prepare.</p>
            <p>From what is here ſaid, there is an eaſie digreſſion to the other part of the Diſquiſition (<hi>how Reaſon is laid aſide</hi> in ſome acts of Faith (a queſtion which much exerciſed the <hi>Reconciler</hi>) whilſt it doth not follow the dictates of its own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, but gives it ſelf up to the guidance of another, <hi>(the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine knowledg)</hi> which advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſupplies natures defect, which makes way for this conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>viz.</hi> Reaſon in ſome caſes is
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:98034:92"/>as much and may as properly be ſaid to be <hi>laid aſide,</hi> as a Judg who is limited by his Monarch, that he may not paſs ſentence in all caſes on his own judgment, but in ſome muſt conſult and follow the dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the ſupreme Magiſtrate, by doing of which he is ſo far <hi>laid aſide,</hi> that as to that particular caſe, he may not ſo properly be called <hi>Judg</hi> as a <hi>Proclaimer</hi> of Juſtice determined by his Superiour. And for the illuſtration, I cannot but inſert a ſtory which I borrow from an Eminent Mathematician who ſays, a Judg puzled with a Caſe of two perſons who had made ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change of <hi>Fields</hi> which were <hi>Iſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimeters,</hi> or of equal ſides but different figures, one a <hi>Rombus</hi> or
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:98034:92"/>
               <hi>oblique Angled,</hi> the other <hi>a ſquare or right Angled parallelogram,</hi> was neceſſitated to call a <hi>Geometri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian</hi> to diſcover the Cheat, which diſcovery in ſtrictneſs was enough to call the Mathematician <hi>Judg,</hi> though the ſentence was pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by <hi>another.</hi> This is applicable to the Spiritual method of impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the underſtanding and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining the Will in matters of faith, if God be conſidered as the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to inform Reaſon which is defective, and as ignorant as the Judg in the former Caſe.</p>
            <p>From this inſtance 'tis plain and eaſie to imagine how advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly Reaſon is <hi>laid aſide,</hi> being diverted from its uſual method in giving aſſent to propoſitions
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:98034:93"/>(which are true) yet in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves not ſufficiently evident, now <hi>evidence</hi> of the truth to the Soul in its pure naturals is ſo neceſſary, that there is no <hi>aſſent</hi> certain with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, but it is otherwiſe in the act of ſaith, when <hi>Divine Teſtimony</hi> ſupplies the place of <hi>natural evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</hi> If it be urged that Reaſon proceeds according to it's own <hi>principles,</hi> and when it ſubmits to the <hi>Divine Teſtimony,</hi> 'tis becauſe Reaſon is informed by Revelation, That it is not a Competent Judge of Religious Myſteries; yet that aſſent being guided by the <hi>Divine Teſtimony</hi> inſtead of <hi>evidence,</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting the faculties of the Soul from their uſual method, is enough to aſſert, <hi>Reaſons being laid aſide.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="167" facs="tcp:98034:93"/>
            <p>Yet this will not make way for a cavilling complaint, that the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine determination doth violence to the faculties whilſt thus diverted from their uſual method, for the <hi>Divine concurſe</hi> which determines them, can no more be ſaid to do vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence, than the <hi>Mathematicians</hi> information of the Judge in the former caſe can be called compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion when he prevailed with him to paſs true ſentence, which he without the Artiſt could not have pronounc't.</p>
            <p>It is not neceſſary that matters of belief are clearly and diſtinctly underſtood, for faith takes its name from <hi>perſwaſion</hi> (which is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways begotten by demonſtration,) and from aſſent more than from the
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:98034:94"/>manner how it is wrought; for the Divine method hath ſeveral ways to command belief, ſometimes it makes an <hi>extempore Convert,</hi> grace working effectually in a moment, ſometimes it operates through the whole courſe of mans life to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the work. It is enough that men are aſſured that their aſſent is terminated in <hi>truth,</hi> becauſe of the Divine determination which makes the Will like the Load-ſtone (which inſtance is much uſed by the Reconciler) which will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly conduct the Mariner, though he knows not how it is directed, whether by a <hi>materia ſubtilis,</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing through the <hi>poles</hi> of this <hi>low vortex,</hi> or any other myſterious way of nature. To ſpeak all, if
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:98034:94"/>
               <hi>Sailing</hi> had been <hi>laid aſide</hi> till the Pilot could demonſtrate its <hi>infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble direction</hi> from its cauſes, the greater part of the World would have been unknown, and the <hi>terra incognita</hi> would take more room in the Mapp than the known part of the World: The ſame may be concluded of faith, for if all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief was to be ſuſpended until the manner how it was wrought was explained, a great part of the World would paſs as Infidels.</p>
            <p>Thus far the infirmity of the mere <hi>natural ſight</hi> hath been diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, it now remains that I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire in what ſenſe the Reconciler, who urgeth belief as an <hi>Act of Prudence,</hi> by which if he only underſtand a rational choice ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:98034:95"/>grace, the former diſcourſe will equally conclude againſt <hi>him</hi> and the Reaſoner. For if a man endued with natural Prudence, muſt neceſſarily embrace the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, becauſe its contents are ſuch as will command aſſent from the Reaſonable man, he ſhuts out Grace in the <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> and makes the Holy Scriptures more <hi>ſufficient,</hi> and in another ſenſe than ever they were ſaid to be (for which they are ſaid to be ſo (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by <hi>Athanaſius, Cyril,</hi> and other holy Fathers) it is to ſhew they are <hi>ſelf-ſufficient</hi> without the ſubſidies of Traditions not in any other ſenſe; for although it muſt be granted that the propoſal of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:98034:95"/>is enough to condemn the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidel as imprudent; yet this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation may not be juſtified on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe the evidence of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was not allow'd, for it is more than probable that the neglect of Petitioning for Grace, and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it when offered, to help unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, doth adjuſt the ſeverity of that ſaying, <hi>He who believes not ſhall be damn'd.</hi> Natural Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is not a ſufficient qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the imbracing Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, if we take it in <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> ſenſe, who defines it an habitual knowledg which can diſcern what is <hi>good</hi> and what is <hi>evil</hi> as they have relation to practice. <hi>lib. Sexto Ethicor. ad Nicom.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <pb n="172" facs="tcp:98034:96"/>
            <p>Prudence thus defin'd can have no place as Antecedent to belief, becauſe that mere Reaſon in ſeveral Caſes cannot judge, what is <hi>good</hi> for man, and what <hi>evil,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will demur at ſome duties ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary for the attaining of happineſs, ſuch as are <hi>ſelf-denial</hi> and other injunctions which natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral prudence will not chooſe, if left to its own evidence. And if it be conſidered as ſubſequent to belief, there is no need of it in diſcerning what is good in practice and what is evil, for duties in Religion are <hi>indiſpenſably</hi> enjoyned, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyes <hi>conſultation,</hi> which deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minates a man <hi>Prudent.</hi> I ſhall
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:98034:96"/>conclude this particular with Chriſt's deciding the Controverſie by ranking the <hi>Prudent man,</hi> in this ſenſe not ſo <hi>wiſe as a Babe,</hi> without Divine aſſiſtance. And when it is taken in a better ſenſe, Divine direction and concurſe is ſuppos'd as neceſſary to ſupply the defect of the mind (and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may challenge the Etymology which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> gives of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> whilſt he calls it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) which God alone is able to do, <hi>and make men wiſe unto Salvation.</hi> Add to this another conſideration, that a <hi>Prudential choice</hi> of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſuppoſes it and its reward too, to be expoſed as a <hi>prize,</hi> not in the Apoſtlical ſenſe. So that he who hath the greateſt ſtock of Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:98034:97"/>muſt paſs as moſt Religious, when he who hath the leaſt, be eſteem'd a Reprobate.</p>
            <p>From all that is ſaid I ſhall only infer this concluſion, ſeeing our eye-ſight needs alteration and it ſelf is indiſpos'd, the Believer doth ſafely reſign himſelf to the conduct of the <hi>All-ſeeing-eye,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Rule of a ſevere Philoſopher (who would not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any truth, but upon the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Reaſon) who ſays, we may in ſome Caſes as ſafely truſt others as our ſelves, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Ariſt. lib. Sext. Ethic. ad Nicom.</hi> So far as men follow an unerring conduct, ſo far they are infallible, though they are not their own Leaders.</p>
            <pb n="175" facs="tcp:98034:97"/>
            <p>Hitherto Reaſon hath been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderd as it is in a ſingle perſon, but the following Diſquiſition conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it in a multitude, or an Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly as it attends their <hi>Sacred Votes,</hi> by which it is made more infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, than when as a Monarch, it aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts its ſeeming priviledges by renouncing all manner of aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in drawing concluſions, but only that, which were nature af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords, relying on private evidence, which alſo is ſuppos'd in every particular Member of a Council. Therefore it is proper to examine <hi>whether Reaſon only, inlightned by apprehending the ſtory and contents of the old and new Teſtaments, is capable of appeals made to it as Judg, and the laſt determiner of
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:98034:98"/>Controverſies, ſo as it can paſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible judgment on propoſitions offer'd as Revelation: And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the fallibility of ſome Councils renders all ſo ſuſpicious that the Chriſtian cannot ſafely rely on Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliary definitions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt branch of this inquiry is affirmed by the Reaſoner, and the other he will not have deny'd, becauſe it makes way for the proof of the former, for by infinuating that all Councils are fallible, he preſumes he may as well appeal to a <hi>fallible ſelf,</hi> as a <hi>fallible multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</hi> But this aſſertion may be checkt from this conſideration; That there is much difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween theſe propoſitions; <hi>General Councils may err;</hi> And, <hi>All have
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:98034:98"/>been and are lyable to Error.</hi> If the latter is granted, it will deſtroy the certainty of a viſible Church at any time ſince it was founded, if not the being of any truly ſo called. For that principle which obligeth a man to believe, that all Councils have been fallible, will never put him out of doubt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the profeſſion of the Church at any time was agreeable to the truth of Religion. For ſeeing the Reaſoners rule admits of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing as certain, further than it is knowable by ſome faculty of the Soul, independent form Divine aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, it is impoſſible that he can have any more than <hi>conjectural knowledg,</hi> Reaſon being not able to inform him of a <hi>Criterion</hi> of a
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:98034:99"/>true Church by its own evidence, but by Revelation, which ſays the <hi>true faith ſhall not fail.</hi> Now that this true faith is in a doubtful caſe, muſt be determin'd by thoſe who have power from God to make a certain diſcovery of it. That which is ſaid, is ſo agreeable to the Apoſtolical rule, <hi>no Scripture is of private interpretation,</hi> (which muſt be confeſt by the Reaſoner, though there was no Sacred Authority to confirm that Canon) that it is only neceſſary that objections are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd. The firſt of which may be this, that by the delivery of Reaſon in private perſons to be determin'd by that which prevails in a multitude, is to make or ſet up a <hi>Rational Papacy.</hi> For as each
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:98034:99"/>Member of the Roman Church is no further eſteem'd Orthodox than he delivers up his private rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon either to the <hi>Pope alone,</hi> or as he is in <hi>juncto</hi> with a general Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, which is ſaid to have ſuch power to determine infallibly, though the interpretation make <hi>Scripture</hi> to be no <hi>Scripture;</hi> So every Chriſtian is to be eſteem'd Orthodox or Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical according to the ſenſe of the Council, which hath power to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret and make his <hi>reaſon</hi> to be no <hi>reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No ſuch concluſion can follow, and if it did, it would not break the force of the arguments, which confirm the former poſitions. For ſuppoſe the <hi>Definitions</hi> of Councils as <hi>concluſions,</hi> which Reaſon draws
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:98034:100"/>from the <hi>premiſes,</hi> nor as none can be ſo raſh as to ſay, Reaſon makes the <hi>concluſion</hi> true which was ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, (only it could not commend it to the <hi>will</hi> and <hi>underſtanding,</hi> as an object of <hi>natural faith,</hi> till the <hi>two propoſitions</hi> were brought as <hi>witneſſes</hi> of the truth of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion,) or that <hi>Logick</hi> creates truth, but only aſſiſts the inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in its ſearch for it; ſo by the ſame reaſon none may ſay, that Councils make Articles of true Religion, though they are the means of their diſcovery.</p>
            <p>But let this objection be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd as it relates to <hi>Papal Decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals.</hi> The name Pope will never affright the ſober man out of that reverence which is due to juſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:98034:100"/>
               <hi>Councils and holy Synods,</hi> or if it be found to be ſo in a <hi>ſingle perſon.</hi> For if it could be prov'd (as ſome have affirm'd) that the Pope was and is the <hi>Church Virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al,</hi> it would be beyond diſpute, that infallibility did at ſome time ſince Chriſtian Religion was in the World, ſit in the <hi>Chair,</hi> or at leaſt may do, when fundamental con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies ariſe, which threaten the Churches ruine without the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of making <hi>Scripture to be no Scripture</hi> by his Authority. It may be ſafely ſaid by any Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, that he would not give aſſent to ſeveral Doctrines which are urg'd as matters of faith neceſſarily to be believ'd for the attaining Salvation, did not the Church declare them to
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:98034:101"/>be ſo; yet the ſame perſon on the ſame principle is not oblig'd to think, that which is ſo defin'd by the Church is made true by its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition. Hitherto I have us'd this compariſon (which makes the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations of Councils as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions of a Syllogiſm made by the <hi>Heads of the World</hi>) to illuſtrate the anſwer to an objection; but it being ſo appoſit to another deſign, it ſhall be us'd to ſhew, that the Reaſoner in a Council is not capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of making a Syllogiſm from mere <hi>natural Topicks</hi> to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the truth of that which is debated. This will appear to be true from the conſideration of the Structure of a Syllogiſm, which leads us to the knowledg of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition,
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:98034:101"/>which was leſs known, by others which are more evident, and eaſie to be underſtood. For the <hi>medium</hi> (which is an ingredient of both propoſitions) is as clear and as certain as a <hi>common notion,</hi> and the truth of the concluſion depends on it, which if <hi>miſtaken,</hi> makes the Syllogiſm a <hi>fallacy.</hi> Suppoſe therefore the Members of a Council as ſo many <hi>Scholaſticks</hi> arguing, they have no ſuch <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon notions</hi> as Philoſophers have, by which as <hi>media,</hi> they can draw concluſions. Although it muſt be confeſt that the <hi>underſtanding</hi> by its <hi>own evidence</hi> can judg of the truth of ſome propoſitions (<hi>viz. It is impoſſible, God can do any act which implyes a contradiction,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:98034:102" rendition="simple:additions"/>Yet Divine Revelation is the <hi>medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> by which truth in propoſitions, which are more obſcure, is deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined. Hence it ſollows that the <hi>Sanctions</hi> and <hi>Definitions</hi> of Councils muſt be ſaid to be <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetically pronounc'd true,</hi> as this ſaying is, <hi>viz.</hi> If the Moon is Eclipſed, the Earth interpoſeth it ſelf between it and the Sun. Not unlike this is the way of arguing in a Council, which proves Chriſt's humanity from his Paſſion; for if he ſuffereth, humane nature did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe it ſelf, elſe he could not ſuffer. Now as none will ſay, there is and always was aneceſſity not in the nature of the Moon, but in the manner of its motion, that it muſt be Eclipſed at ſome times (for to
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:98034:102"/>ſay ſo, is to confine the Almighty's wiſdom to one <hi>Syſtem,</hi> and to take away the poſſibility of the Worlds being in ſuch a frame in which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sun or Moon might be Eclipſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) but when it is ſeen to be ſo, it is evident, that the Earths <hi>interpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is the <hi>cauſe</hi> of that ſeeming defect. So a Council cannot conclude the neceſſity of <hi>Chriſts</hi> being <hi>Man</hi> but <hi>Hypothetically;</hi> For the <hi>Divine decrees</hi> (which reaſon cannot know but by Revelation) are as the <hi>condition</hi> or <hi>antecedent</hi> which makes <hi>Chriſt's humanity</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary. Let not this aſſertion ſeem ſtrange, ſince it is impoſſible, but that reaſon muſt be defective as it appears from the former inſtance, as alſo from this conſideration, that
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:98034:103"/>the mere Reaſoner cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the neceſſity of Chriſts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation, and will be more at a loſs in other myſterious matters of faith. The definitions and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions of Councils thus hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetically drawn are not leſs cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, becauſe they are ſuch, ſeeing the <hi>Antecedents</hi> of their <hi>propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> are <hi>matters of fact</hi> contain'd in holy Scriptures, and thoſe who diſcourſe, have Divine aſſiſtance in diſcerning the <hi>connexion</hi> and infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the <hi>conſequences;</hi> Now the <hi>connexion</hi> and <hi>ſequel</hi> is true, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the Divine direction, as is already prov'd, and the <hi>Antecedent, viz.</hi> matters of fact, is ſo, as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears from the miracles which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd their truth, which were ſuch
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:98034:103"/>as reaſon might diſcern to be Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine; for Reaſon may be allow'd a Judg in this caſe, though not in all doubts which come under de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate in a Council. The reaſon of which is this, Miracles being works which exceed mere natural power or ordinary courſe of nature, it is furniſhed with faculties which can diſcern what is natural, and what not, but is at a loſs in higher my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries.</p>
            <p>This aſſertion perhaps may be checkt by an inſtance in <hi>conciliary</hi> proceedings in diſcerning <hi>Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Books</hi> of Holy Scripture from <hi>Apocryphal,</hi> or any falſly ſo called, in which, judgment is paſt by mere rational evidence, whilſt it diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth the one from the other by
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:98034:104"/>their <hi>Contents.</hi> This muſt not be granted; for though the <hi>contents of Holy Scriptures</hi> are a good argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their truth; yet they are not the only <hi>Characteriſticks</hi> to diſtinguiſh them from others which are not <hi>Canonical.</hi> When there is any debate in a Council concerning any part of Scripture to be admitted into Canon, appeals are not made to mere Reaſon to judg of its contents, any further than by compariſon of them with thoſe of other Books, which are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived without any controverſie. It is the Councils buſineſs to argue as the Apoſtolical Canon ſays <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and the Church of <hi>England</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes the definitions of Councils
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:98034:104"/>deductions of Reaſon (<hi>Artic.</hi> 21) which admits of this limitation or rather interpretation, that though Reaſon draws the conclusſions; yet their truth is not meaſur'd by a <hi>bare congruity</hi> to it, but the recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it in the primitive Church, or the moſt <hi>free</hi> and <hi>unbiaſſed Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils,</hi> and ſo much of its as belongs to the Old Teſtament by the <hi>Jewiſh Catalogue,</hi> and by ſeveral other Rules, which are as a <hi>Touchſtone</hi> to diſcover Gold, and diſtinguiſh it from baſer Mettals. To ſpeak all, <hi>Conciliary Diſcuſſions</hi> in this caſe do not inquire how Revelation is agreeable to Reaſon, but what is to be admitted as Revelation, and what to be rejected, and when that is done, compare one Text with
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:98034:105"/>another till they agree, which <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> is the moſt <hi>infallible evidence</hi> of truth. However it is ſcarce probable, that the Reaſoner will be perſwaded or argued out of his pretended private infallibility, whilſt he concludes, every indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual man may proceed on the ſame ground which <hi>Councils</hi> do, becauſe each rational man being in ſome degree more or leſs able to draw concluſions by Analogy, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring the ſeveral <hi>contents of Holy Scriptures.</hi> Wherefore let it be ſuppos'd, that each reaſonable man is naturally qualified to find truth; yet ſeeing the promiſe of Divine aſſiſtance (which is the moſt ſure foundation on which infallibility can reſt) is not to a <hi>ſingle perſon,</hi>
               <pb n="191" facs="tcp:98034:105"/>thoſe <hi>natural qualifications</hi> cannot aſſure them of finding it.</p>
            <p>I am ſenſible that the Reaſoner may take occaſion from what is ſaid of urging a queſtion, whether the former aſſertion doth take the priviledge from every private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſo that in any caſe he cannot interpret Scripture.</p>
            <p>The affirmative of this queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may be ſafely maintain'd as it hath reſpect to private perſons who are known Members of the Church, and have opportunity of being acquainted with, and to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, what is the interpretation and ſenſe of the Church in general, which muſt be a direction to thoſe who paſs judgment in particular caſes, for they may not appeal from
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:98034:106"/>Synods to their own private reaſon, and becauſe truth is certainly to be found in Councils, and there are Rules of finding it.</p>
            <p>If it is further demanded, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a private perſon who hath nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther learning or opportunity to underſtand the ſenſe of the Church, may not be a ſafe inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter of Scripture in order to his own Satisfaction and Salvation?</p>
            <p>As this propoſes an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary caſe, ſo the anſwer may be dubiouſly return'd. However it may be ſaid to the firſt part of the queſtion, that it cannot be well ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, that any illiterate perſon ſhould of neceſſity be ignorant of the ſenſe of the Church, ſeeing he is a <hi>known Member</hi> of the ſame,
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:98034:106"/>and the <hi>paſtors</hi> are as <hi>Mouths</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it. To the other part of the queſtion, which ſuppoſes a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſo unfortunately (amongſt the Infidels) plac't, that he cannot have acceſs to <hi>Paſtors</hi> of the Church, it is enough to propoſe another queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi> Whether the Thief on the Croſs who may be ſuppoſed to want time (though nothingmore could be wanting whilſt Chriſt was with him) did give aſſent to all fundamentals of Religion by faith as <hi>explicit</hi> as is required of other Chiſtians who have the advantage of more time and other circumſtances? The anſwer given to this will help the ſolution of the other doubt.</p>
            <p>The manner of <hi>Conciliary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings</hi>
               <pb n="194" facs="tcp:98034:107"/>being conſidered, and the unfitneſs of the mere reaſoner for ſuch debates: in he next place the neceſſity of Councils ſhall be prov'd, by which the other part of the Diſquiſition will be better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood.</p>
            <p>Such <hi>Sacred Aſsemblies</hi> are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, though not at all times (for ſome ages paſs't without them) for the exigency of the Church requires ſuch ſupplies. To ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin it could always be without them, is to conclude it exempt from all poſſibility of erring, and independent as to the Divine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, which is promis'd to <hi>lead it</hi> and <hi>continue it</hi> in the way of truth; The former cannot be granted, for Hereſies <hi>muſt be,</hi> and then there is as
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:98034:107"/>great neceſſity of their condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The latter cannot be allow'd, for as it intrenches on the <hi>Divine Dominion,</hi> ſo it doth equalize the <hi>Church Militant</hi> with the <hi>Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant,</hi> whoſe greateſt Trimuph is ovr Error.</p>
            <p>This neceſſity of Councils is confirm'd from the conſideration of different opinions concerning <hi>matters</hi> of <hi>faith,</hi> which equally commend themſelves to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and render his <hi>Will</hi> ſo <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different,</hi> that he knows not to which part to incline, till determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Authority. It is no ſtrange thing to meet with two opinions in other caſes, which plead for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with ſuch equal probability, that the moſt accurate judgment
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:98034:108"/>will rather ſuſpend its belief, than give aſſent to either; neither let it appear a prodigy, if Religion afford ſuch caſes as would render its <hi>proſelytes</hi> or <hi>profeſſors ſceptically</hi> puzled without a more <hi>infallible guide</hi> than their own Reaſon.</p>
            <p>But it may be ſaid, that in other caſes the wiſe men do not give themſelves up to a <hi>Sect</hi> or <hi>Council</hi> of Philoſophers to be <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mpires</hi> in dubious matters. This is granted, for it is unreaſonable that they ſhould deliver up their Reaſon to the moſt fam'd Sophies, but the reaſon is not the ſame in Religious debates. For a ſingle perſon may be qualifi'd for finding truth in Philoſophy, with ſuch certainty as may vie with the numerous <hi>Sects;</hi>
               <pb n="197" facs="tcp:98034:108"/>but no private member of the Church may pretend to that cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty which muſt be allow'd in Councils. It is poſſible that one man may be maſter of more reaſon and Philoſophy than is to be found in all the World at that time, and one <hi>walking Library</hi> more valuable than a <hi>Vatican;</hi> but Religious knowledg is not deſign'd to be ſo <hi>Monastical</hi> as to live in ſolitude or a ſingle perſon. Beſides, if it could be prov'd that the Philoſophers had the ſame aſſurance of a true conduct in their doubts by <hi>reaſon,</hi> which the <hi>Councils</hi> have by <hi>Divine ſupplies,</hi> he would be unreaſonable in a high degree who would not give up or reſign his private rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to their determinations.</p>
            <pb n="198" facs="tcp:98034:109"/>
            <p>The <hi>great aſſertor</hi> of the Roman Church (<hi>D. Stap.</hi>) was not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether miſtaken when he introduc't Divine aſſiſtance to help the Church in making a Syllogiſm (though the manner of its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyance ſeems inconſiſtent, whilſt he makes the Members of it to be <hi>diſcurſive</hi> in the <hi>premifes</hi> as mere Reaſoners, but <hi>infallibly aſſiſted</hi> in the <hi>concluſion</hi>) for Revelation muſt take place of pure natural inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the whole matter of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious debates.</p>
            <p>That there is a neceſſity of the Reſignation of Reaſon to Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty muſt be granted, and it is urg'd by ſeveral methods. Two late Authors (who <hi>conſider'd</hi> and <hi>exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd humane</hi> Reaſon) endeavour
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:98034:109"/>to convince men of the neceſſity of giving up our private reaſon to the publick judgment of other perſons, <hi>who have better means of knowing of truth than we our ſelves have,</hi> as one expreſſeth it, and both preſs it by an inſtance of an <hi>appeal in naturals from ſenſe to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi> This way of arguing may be perſwaſive, but not cogent enough to evince men of the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of that which they deſign'd to prove; for although it is ſafely concluded that the Members of Councils have better qualifications for diſcovery of truth than private perſons; yet their learning and natural endowments are not that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or the foundation on which faith is laid.</p>
            <pb n="200" facs="tcp:98034:110"/>
            <p>Beſides the ſimilitude of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals from <hi>Senſe</hi> to <hi>Reaſon</hi> is not appoſit, and implies a ſuppoſition of the ſenſes being erroneous, which in ſtrictneſs cannot be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd, but let that be ſuppos'd, it cannot well be accommodated to the caſe, for ſenſe and reaſon in man are not ſo much ſtrangers as the publick <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> of the Church in Councils are to its par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Members. The ſame <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipient</hi> is imploy'd in reaſon and ſenſe, and according to its diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent acts and objects hath diſtinct compellations, <hi>ſenſual</hi> or <hi>rational,</hi> as the ſame River takes ſeveral names from the Channels through which it runs. For when the Soul perceives <hi>material impreſſes</hi> on the
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:98034:110"/>Brain without any conſideration or <hi>reflex act,</hi> it is call'd <hi>ſenſation</hi> (as when it perceives a body as it is figur'd in that part which nature deſign'd for Phancy, to be <hi>Trian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular</hi> or <hi>Globular, red</hi> or <hi>white,</hi> or as it is repreſented in other figures or colours) but when it deliberates and draws concluſions, ſuch as cannot be the work or reſult of a naked repreſentation of the object, it challengeth its juſt title <hi>rational.</hi> Now to ſuppoſe this ſimilitude ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly appoſit, is to conclude that every <hi>private perſon</hi> ſhould have his Soul imployd and acting (as <hi>junto</hi> which cannot be imagin'd) in every particular debate of a Council as the <hi>percipient</hi> is in ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation and Reaſoning.</p>
            <pb n="202" facs="tcp:98034:111"/>
            <p>More arguments might be urg'd to evince the neceſſity of Councils, but I do not intend to be ſo volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minous, but to paſs to another in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry concerning truth and its cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of being ſo, as it is in lawful Councils. Satisfaction will be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to this inquiry, if it is conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derd that <hi>the true faith was once delivered to the Saints as St.</hi> Jude ſays, and what that true faith is may be found in ſome conciliary Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions ſince Chriſt's coming into the World, and that it may be ſafely concluded, that it is found when there is a general conſent, which is an infallible <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and as certain as any <hi>medium</hi> in Demonſtration. Suppoſe one true opinion in Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy and a Thouſand in which
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:98034:111"/>there is truth, but mixt with error; If they all agree in ſome poſitions it is an undoubted argument of the truth of thoſe in which all agree. This way of paſſing judgment on Definitions of Councils upon exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination will appear as certain as that which draws concluſions from this rule. <hi>Quoe in aliquo tertio con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniunt inter ſe conveniunt.</hi> That trite ſaying <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is more than a proverbial concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for it is founded in reaſon, which muſt conclude error hath many <hi>Moeanders</hi> and <hi>diſtracting paths:</hi> but truth hath a <hi>narrow way,</hi> in which only it ſelf can walk. And it muſt needs be ſo for this reaſon; truth being in ſome <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliary Definitions,</hi> they muſt be
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:98034:112"/>as the <hi>Center</hi> in which, all which are true, neceſſarily meet. If it is ſaid, that it is poſſible that thoſe <hi>Definitions,</hi> which are to be as a <hi>Standard</hi> to meaſure others, may not be found, the Church being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frauded or abus'd by misfortune or cunning, and conſequently at a loſs in the ſearch for truth, as much as he who ſails without a <hi>Compaſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This cannot be ſuppos'd becauſe of the Divine promiſe of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the <hi>truefaith,</hi> though not at all times diſcoverable. But let it be imagin'd that ſome <hi>true Conciliary Definitions</hi> may be wanting, then the <hi>ſuppoſition</hi> is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd, which implyes a <hi>Catholick conſent,</hi> which cannot be ſo call'd, if but one Definition is left out:
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:98034:112"/>Therefore it may be concluded that Truth is to be found by this Method; though with as much difficulty as <hi>Archimedes</hi> diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Gold, and the quantity of it in his Princes Crown, which a <hi>Cheat</hi> had <hi>Adulterated</hi> with baſer Metals.</p>
            <p>Religion therefore being in its own frame and nature fitted for the ſevereſt Inquiſition, it will not ſtand in fear of the boldeſt Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary, Authority in its name bids the Reaſoner be modeſt, and its matter which it injoyns further commands him to be ſo, whilſt he ſpeaks of that which tranſcends his underſtanding. It may now ſeem proper to ſuggeſt theſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments which ſeem to invalidate
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:98034:113"/>Authority, and render it leſs valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; This is done by objecting the errors of Councils, and the manner of their Proceſs by <hi>Votes</hi> or <hi>Suffrages;</hi> the firſt of which ſeems to inſinuate to the Chriſtian, the poſibility of the body of the Church being altogether diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jointed, and its total Apoſtacy with the ſame reaſon that a man may conclude that man-kind cannot be exempt from the poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of being <hi>Cripples,</hi> becauſe that <hi>ſome bones</hi> have been out of their <hi>proper place,</hi> and the other ſeems to render them more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, by comparing them with <hi>Proceſses of Courts</hi> which are <hi>purely humane;</hi> both theſe are as eaſily confuted as named, and may
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:98034:113"/>be more effectually retorted on reaſon, as it is exerciſed in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ways of Government in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ages. For the former obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is removed in the precedent Diſquiſition, and the other will appear to be weak and diſabled, if it is conſidered that <hi>Votes</hi> and <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frages</hi> in holy Councils are as Lots in the choice of an Apoſtle, which having <hi>infallible Direction</hi> from God may vie certainty with a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree or any way of Election. <hi>Matthias</hi> was no leſs an <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> neither was his Authority more doubted, with which he was inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by Lots, than that of the other Apoſtles, who had an <hi>oral miſſion</hi> from Chriſt himſelf. I might further aſſert Eccleſiaſtical
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:98034:114"/>Authority, by ſhewing the ſafety of relying on the Authority of Councils with a more firm aſſent than Hiſtory or the humane Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver can challenge; For the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian (I mean the profane) commits not Annals to poſterity upon peril of his own ruine, in caſe ſome cunning and political inventions be interwoven in them like ſome of the Hiſtory which <hi>Zenophon</hi> wrote, which ſeems more like a Romance than an impartial Relation of <hi>Cyrus</hi> his Life and Education; and thoſe who give precepts to other men, ſometimes have a reſerve of immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and exemption from them to themſelves: But holy Councils have no ſuch equivocation, which though it may ſeem <hi>pious deceit,</hi>
               <pb n="209" facs="tcp:98034:114"/>cannot ſit ſafely in <hi>Sacred Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies,</hi> neither may any Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of them as an <hi>Arian</hi> profeſs one, and carry another <hi>Creed</hi> in his Boſome: were it poſſible that any Member of a true Council might do this ſafely and without peril of his own ruine, <hi>Conciliary Definitions</hi> might be rendered more ſuſpicious, but the caſe is otherwiſe in ſuch Sacred debates, the Members of Councils as well as private perſons of the Church are like St. <hi>Paul</hi> and his <hi>Company</hi> in the Ship which could not be ſecured from the Tempeſt, <hi>If all were not ſaved,</hi> or at leaſt in a capacity of being ſo, for as the Apoſtle might not eſcape upon a
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:98034:115"/>Planck alone; neither may the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick repreſentatives of the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Church</hi> promiſe themſelves Salvation, it they willingly define any ſuch matters of faith to the people as may indanger the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Shipwrack of a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience relying on their Authority. For thoſe who out of deſign define error as matters of faith, are in equal danger, if not more, with thoſe who put their <hi>Definitions</hi> in practice.</p>
            <p>Hence appears the certainty of that knowledg which is the effect of faith, which as much exceeds that which is purely humane, as <hi>Science</hi> doth <hi>Opinion,</hi> which is ſuch a low and fickle degree of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:98034:115"/>as ſeems ſuited for trifling things below Heavenly objects; for God hath diſpoſed of Religious matters in ſuch manner, as that a man may know God, and be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd of his own duty with as great certainty, if not greater, than he can know the objects of <hi>natural Science.</hi> For the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence which the Schools make be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Faith and Science conſiſts not only in the <hi>certainty</hi> of the one being greater than the other, but in the <hi>manner</hi> of <hi>Evidence</hi> in the objects, which occaſions the grand cavil againſt faith, as being an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable peice of ſervice im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd on man, and <hi>which is to give aſſent to that which cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:98034:116"/>it ſelf to the underſtanding with ſufficient evidence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this is urged, it may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted upon <hi>Science,</hi> for if nothing muſt command aſſent (as it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid) but what is <hi>clearly and diſtinctly perceiv'd, Euclid</hi>'s De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations muſt be leſs in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and more maim'd; and there will be only the name of Science of many things left in the world. Beſides there is no reaſon of complaint of want of <hi>evidence</hi> in the act of faith, for it is <hi>evidence enough, that the mind is inform'd that it cannot comprehend its ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, however it ought to give aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</hi> Let this be made more plain by a ſuppoſition: Suppoſe a
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:98034:116"/>
               <hi>Terra incognita</hi> (I do not mean that which Geographers call ſo, for that in future ages may have a new name in the Map) or ſome part of the world was ſo deſign'd and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triv'd by the Creator, that it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible it ſhould be known: Or ſuppoſe there were <hi>Planetary Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions habitable,</hi> but not intended to be diſcover'd clearly to man, 'tis enough in this feigned caſe, that men are inform'd that there are ſuch places, and advis'd of the impoſſibility that they ſhould be known. This fiction is applicable to more ſerious and Religious caſes, and may ſtop the mouths of a querulous <hi>Generation of ſeekers,</hi> who are content with a low degree
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:98034:117"/>of knowledg, which doth not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell opinion in certainty, which kind of knowledg was ſo little eſteem'd amongſt ſome of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, that it was plac't by them in the <hi>imagination,</hi> rather than the <hi>underſtanding,</hi> as better ſuiting with the condition of <hi>Brutes</hi> than <hi>men.</hi> 'Tis true the Schools have been more kind and curteous to <hi>Opinion,</hi> and give it a place in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> but being there according to their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of it, <hi>ſits trembling and in fear it may be deceiv'd, and that which it apprehends to be true may be falſe;</hi> This conſider'd will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt faith (which in a looſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, may be call'd Reaſon
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:98034:117"/>Divinely aſſiſted and directed) above mere carnal Reaſonings, and juſtifie the challenge which St. <hi>Paul</hi> makes in his Chriſtian Armour, <hi>where is the Diſputer of the World?</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
